<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anno primo &amp; secundo Philippi &amp; Mariæ. Actes made at a Parliament, begon and holde[n] at Westminster, the. xii. daye of Nouember, in the fyrste and seconde yeare of the reigne of our soueraygne lorde, and lady Philip and Mary, by the grace of God, kinge [and] Quene of England, Fraunce, Naples, Ierusalem, and Ireland, defendours of the fayth, Princes of Spayne and Cycilie, Archedukes of Austria, dukes of Myllayn, Burgondie, and Braband, counties of Haspurge, Flau[n]ders and Tyroll, and there continued and kept to the dissolution of the same, beynge the. xvi. day of Ianuary then next ensuynge, were enacted as foloweth. Cum priuilegio Regiæ Maiestatis·</title>
            <title>Public General Acts. 1553-1555. 1-2 Philip and Mary</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1553-1558 : Mary I)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1555</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 193 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74038</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 9447.8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124844</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900335</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900335</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150877</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74038)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150877)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1985:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anno primo &amp; secundo Philippi &amp; Mariæ. Actes made at a Parliament, begon and holde[n] at Westminster, the. xii. daye of Nouember, in the fyrste and seconde yeare of the reigne of our soueraygne lorde, and lady Philip and Mary, by the grace of God, kinge [and] Quene of England, Fraunce, Naples, Ierusalem, and Ireland, defendours of the fayth, Princes of Spayne and Cycilie, Archedukes of Austria, dukes of Myllayn, Burgondie, and Braband, counties of Haspurge, Flau[n]ders and Tyroll, and there continued and kept to the dissolution of the same, beynge the. xvi. day of Ianuary then next ensuynge, were enacted as foloweth. Cum priuilegio Regiæ Maiestatis·</title>
                  <title>Public General Acts. 1553-1555. 1-2 Philip and Mary</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1553-1558 : Mary I)</author>
                  <author>Mary I, Queen of England, 1516-1558.</author>
                  <author>Philip II, King of Spain, 1527-1598.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>xxxiiii leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>in ædibus Iohannis Cawodi, tipographi Regiæ Maiestatis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Excusum Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno M. D. LV. [1555]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Title page has border McKerrow &amp; Ferguson 81.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>In this edition, B2r catchword: 'Prouy-'--STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College Library, Cambridge, England.</note>
                  <note>Early English Books filmed copy missing  D5-D6; with A2 as in 9447.7--STC.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Law --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150877:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno primo &amp; ſecundo Philippi &amp; Mariae.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>ACTES</hi> made at a Parliament, begon and holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Weſtminſter, the .xii. daye of Nouember, in the fyrſte and ſeconde yeare of the reigne of our ſoueraygne Lorde, and Lady Philip and Mary, by the grace of God, kinge &amp; Quene of England, Fraunce, Naples, Ieruſalem, and Ireland, defendours of the fayth, Princes of Spayne and Cycilie, Archedukes of Auſtria, dukes of Myllayn, Burgondie, and Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, counties of Haſpurge, Flau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Tyroll, and there conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued and kept to the diſſolution of the ſame, beynge the .xvi. day of Ianuary then next enſuynge, were enacted as foloweth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio Regiae Maiestatis.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:150877:2"/>
            <head>The Table.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N Acte touchyng letters patentes, &amp; other writinges to be ſigned by the Quenes Maieſtie. Cap. i.</item>
               <item>An acte for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reformation of exceſſe in apparayll. Cap. ii.</item>
               <item>An acce againſt ſeditious wordes &amp; rumours. Cap. iii.</item>
               <item>An acte for the punyſhment of certayne perſons calling them ſelues Egyptians. Cap. iiii.</item>
               <item>An acte for to reſtrayne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> carrying of corne, victualles, and woode o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the ſea. Cap. v.</item>
               <item>An acte for the reuiuing of three Eſtatutes made for the puniſhment of hereſies. Cap. vi.</item>
               <item>An acte that perſons dwelling in the countrye, ſhall not ſell dyuers wares in cities, and Townes corporate by retayle. Cap. vii.</item>
               <item>An acte repealinge all Statutes, articles, and prouiſions, made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the ſea apoſtolike of Rome, ſynce the .xx. yeare of King Henry theight, and alſo for the ſtablyſhment of all ſpirituall, and eccleſiaſtical poſſeſſions, and hereditamentes conueyed to the laytie. Cap. viii.</item>
               <item>An acte for the puniſhment of Traiterous wordes againſt the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Maieſtie. Cap. ix.</item>
               <item>An acte wherby certayne offences be made treaſons, and alſo for the gouernement of the kynges and Quenes maieſties iſſue. Cap. x.</item>
               <item>An acte for the punyſhment of bringinge in of counterfeyte coyne of forr eyne realmes, being curraunt within this realme. Cap. xi.</item>
               <item>An acte touchyng the impounding of diſtreſſes.</item>
               <item>An acte appoynting in ordre to iuſtices of peace touchyng the bayle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of priſoners. Cap. xiii.</item>
               <item>An acte for the makyng of ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, and fuſti an of Naples in Norwiche. Cap. xiiii.</item>
               <item>An acte to confirme the liberties of the Lord-Marchers in Wales. Cap. xv.</item>
               <item>An acte for the continuaunce of certayne ſtatutes. Cap. xvi.</item>
               <item>An acte touchyng leaſes hereafter to be made by certayne ſpirituall perſons. Cap. xvii</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb n="ii" facs="tcp:150877:2"/>
            <head>¶ An Acte touchinge letters patentes, and other Writinges, to be ſigned by the Queenes maieſtie.</head>
            <head type="sub">¶ The firſt Chapter.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEREIN THE</hi> parliament begon and holden at Weſtminſter, the ſeconde day of Aprill, in the firſt yeare of the reygne of our mooſt dread and gratious Soueraygne Ladye the Queenes maieſtie, and there continu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed and kept, tyll the diſſolution of the ſame, beyng the fyft day of May, then next folowynge, one Acte was made touchyng the articles of her highnes moſt noble mariage. In the which act amongeſt other thinges it is enacted, ordred, and eſtablyſhed by aucthoritie of the ſayd parliament, that all and ſinguler giftes, grauntes, letters patentes, eſchaunges, confy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, leaſes, and other writinges, which after the ſaid marriage, and during the ſame, ſhoulde paſſe, and be made of any benefices, offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, landes, reuenues, and fruites, or of any of them, ſhoulde be intite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and made in the names of our Soueraygne Lorde the kyng, and of her mooſt excellent hyghnes, whether his maieſtie ſhoulde be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent within the Realmes and dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of her highnes, or within any of them, or abſent. And that the ſame giftes, grauntes letters paten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, eſchaunges, confirmations, leaſes, and other wrytinges, ſo ſette forth and made, ſhoulde be ſealed, and fyrmed with the ſygne manuel of her highnes, and the ſame ſo ſigned and ſealed with the great ſeale of this realme or with ſuch ſeale as hath bene accuſtomed, ſhuld be by thauctoritie of the ſayde parliament, deemed, adiudged, declared, and pronounced to be as good perfect, and of like force, ſtrength, &amp; effecte in the lawe, to all intentes, conſtructions, and purpoſes, agaynſt our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde Soueraygne Lorde and Lady, the king and the Queenes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties, and her highnes heyres and Succeſſours, as yf her maieſtie had bene at the tyme of the makyng thereof, ſole and vnmarried, and that al gyftes. grauntes, letters patentes, eſechaunges, confirmations leaſes, and other wrytinges, whiche after the ſayde marryage, and durynge the tyme of the ſame, ſhuld paſſe, and be made of the ſayd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, offices, landes, reuenues, and fruites, or of any of them, wher vnto the ſigne manuell, of herhighneſſe, ſhulde not be ſette, made of put, ſhalbe by aucthoritie of the ſayde parliament, from tyme to tyme, deemed, adiudged, accepted, taken, and decreed, to be of no force, ne ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, but vtterly fruſtrate and voyde in the lawe, to all intentes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruccions,
<pb facs="tcp:150877:3"/>and purpoſes, the ſayd marryage, or any law, vſage or cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome to the contrary in any wiſe notwithſtandynge, as by the ſayde Acte more at large doth appeare.</p>
            <p>Sythence the makyng of which Statute, and the ſolemniſation of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde marriage, the Queenes mooſt excellent maieſtie hath bene greatly moleſted, greued, &amp; troubled, with often ſigning of letters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes, gyftes, grauntes, eſchaunges, leaſes, and other wrytynges concerninge and touchyng benefices, offices, landes, reuenues, and fruites, made and graunted by, and from our ſayd ſoueraygne Lorde the kynge, and her hyghneſſe, to ſondry of theyr mooſte louyng ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctes, to whome alſo it hath bene, and is, no ſmal charge to attende vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll ſuche tyme as they may procure and obteyne the ſigne manuel of her highnes, vnto theyr ſayd letters patentes, gyftes grauntes, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaunges, confyrmations, and leaſes, without whiche ſigne, the ſame are vtterly voyde, by force of the ſaid Statute, to the great daunger, loſſe, and vtter vndoyng of diuers perſons, that haue lately bought, purchaſed, or opteyned of our ſayd ſoueraygne Lorde and Lady, the kynge and Quenes maieſties, dyuers landes, tenementes, and other he reditamentes, to theyr great coſtes and charges.</p>
            <p>For remedy wherof be it enacted by the aucthoritie of this preſent parliament, that the ſayd braunche and article, touchinge, or concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng onely the ſigning of letters patentes, gyftes, grauntes, eſchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, confirmations, leaſes, or of other wrytinges for any landes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices, offices, reuenues, fruictes, or other hereditamentes, ſhalbe from henceforth clerely repelled, and made fruſtrate, and voyde, to al intentes, and purpoſes.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by auctoritie of this preſent parliament, that all and ſynguler letters patentes, touchinge, or concernyng any gyfte graunte, eſchaunge, confirmation, leaſe, or other wrytynge, the whiche ſythence the ſayde marriage, hath paſſed, and be made of any benefices, offices, manours, landes, tenementes, reuenues, fruytes, liberties, or other hereditamentes, or of any of them, in the names of our mooſt dread Soueraygne Lorde and Ladye, the kynge and the Quenes maieſties (the warraunt or wryting, or warrauntes or wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges wherof beyng ſigned with her highnes ſigne manuell, in ſuch fourme, ordre, and degree, as the ſame heretofore haue bene accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be ſigned, when her highnes was ſole, and vnmarried) ſhalbe by aucthoritie of this preſent parliament, of the ſame lyke force, ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gthe, and effecte in the law, to all intentes, conſtructions, and purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as yf the ſame were, or had bene ſigned by her highnes ſigne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuell, and as yf her maieſtie had ben at the tyme of the makyng ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſole and vnmarryed, and as they were before the makynge of the ſayde acte. The ſayde eſtatute, or any braunche, or article therin con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned to the contrary in any wyſe, notwithſtandyng.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="iii" facs="tcp:150877:3"/>
            <head>An Acte for the reformation of exceſſe in apparell,</head>
            <head type="sub">¶ The .ii. Chapter.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>E IT</hi> enacted by thauctoritie of this preſente Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that no perſon borne within this realme, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dominions of the ſame, other then the ſonne &amp; heyre apparaunt of a knyght, or other then ſuche, as maye diſpende .xx. li. by the yeare in landes, offices fees, or other yearely reuenues for terme of lyfe, or be worthe in goodes. ii. C. li ſhall after the fyrſte daye of Apryll next comming weare any maner of ſylke, in or vpon, his hatte, bonet night cappe, girdle, ſkaberd, hooſe, ſhoes, or ſpurre lethers, vpon pain of three moneths impriſmo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ent, &amp; forfeytures of .x. li foreuery dayes wearing contrary to the tenour of this acte.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> be it further enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayd, that Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtices of Aſſiſes in theyr circuities, Iuſtices of peace in their ſeſſions, Sheriffes in theyr turnes, Stewardes in letes and lawe daies, Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iors, Sheriffes, and Baylyffes of cities Boroughes, &amp; townes cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate in their courtes, ſhall, and may enquire, heare and determine from time to tyme, al and euery the ſaydoffences, committed, or done wythin the lymites of theyr ſeuerall iuriſdictions, and auethorities, and where any ſuch forfeytures ſhall happen to be founde within the precince of any citie, bourough, towne corporate, lete or lawe daye, then the Maior, Sherife, &amp; Baylyffes of the ſayd cities, boroughes, and townes, and owner of the ſayde lete or lawe dayes, to haue the one moytie of the ſayd forfeytures, and thother moytye to be to any ſubiecte of this realme, that wil ſue for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame in any couct of record by action information, byll, or otherwiſe, in which no wager of lawe protection, or aſſoigne ſhalbe allowed. And where ſuche forfeyture ſhalbe founde oute of any citie, boroughe, towne, lete, or lawe daye that the moytie of all ſuch forfeytures, ſhalbe to the kyng &amp; Queenes maieſtſes, and the heyres to the Quene, and thother moytie thereof to any of theyr ſubiectes, that wyll ſue, for the ſame by byll playnt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, information, or otherwiſe in any court of record, as is aforeſaid, in the which no wager of lawe, or protectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, eſſoigne ſhalbe admitted or allowed. And that all and euery ſuch perſon &amp; perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es, as haue auc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thoritie by vertue of this Acte, to heare and determine the premiſſes may vpon the conuiction of euery ſuch offender, awarde proceſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the Shiriffe of any ſhire within this realme, for the apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the ſayd offendour, which beyng apprehended, ſhalbe commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the ſheriffe vnto the goale of the ſayd ſhire, there to remayne without bayle or maynpryſe vntyll the ſaide offendoure hath payde the ſayd for feyture, wherin he is ſo conuicted.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150877:4"/>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayde, that yf any perſon or perſons, of what eſtate, condition, or degre ſoeuer he or they be after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd fyrſt day of Apryl next commyng, knowyng and ſeruaunte or ſeruauntes of hys or theyrs to offende contrarieto this acte, do not putte the ſame out of his or their ſeruice but ſhall kepe in hys or their ſetuice, the ſame offendoure or offendours by the ſpace of xiiii. dayes, next after ſuche knowledge had, or elles being ſo put out of his or their ſeruice, ſhal retayne the ſame offendour or offendours to his or theyrſeruice agayne within one yeare nextenſuing the time of committing of any ſuch offence, the ſame perſon or perſons, ſo ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng or reteyning agayne, in, or to his or their ſeruice any ſuche ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt or ſeruauntes, offendyng contrary to the tenoure of this acte as is aforeſayd, ſhall for euery his or theyr offence forſayt C.li. of law full monye of Englande, the moytie whereof to be to the kynge and Queenes maieſties vſe and the heyres &amp; ſucceſſours of the Queene, and the other moytie to hym, that wyll ſue for the ſame in any courte of recorde, by action, byll, playnt, information, or otherwiſe wherin no wager of lawe, eſſoygne, or protection ſhalbe admitted or allowed.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alwaye, and be it enacted that thys acte, or any thyng therein contayned, ſhall not extend to any perſon beynge of or aboue the degre of a knyghts ſonne, or doughter, or beinge wyfe to any of them, nor to ſuche as haue bene, be, or ſhalbe Maior, Bayliffe Alderma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or head officer in anye citie borough, or towne corporateor to the wyfe of any of them, nor to anye of the kinges, or Queenes ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes in ordinarie wages attendau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, and wearynge the kinges or Quenes ordinarie liueries, but that they, and euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, may vſe and we are as they, or any of them might lawfully vſe and weare, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the makyng of this acte.</p>
            <p>Prouided alſo that no perſon ſhalbe compelled by this acte, to put awaye his prentiſe or hyred ſeruaunt before thende of the terme before agreed betwene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor that any maſter ſhal forfeyte or looſe any payne or forfayture for the keping of his pre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiſe or hired ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t after his offence contrary to this acte, vnto thende of the terme be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore agreed betwene them Anye thyng aboue ſayd to the contrarye, notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alſo, that women may weare in theyr cappes, hattes, gyrdles, and hoodes, as they or anye of them mighte vſe and wear lawfully before the makyng of thys acte.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An Acte agaynſt ſedicious wordes and rumors.</head>
            <head type="sub">¶ The .iii. Chapiter.</head>
            <pb n="iiii" facs="tcp:150877:4"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here it is conteined as wel in the Statute of Weſtm. the fyrſt, as in the Statute made at Gloceſtre the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde yeare of the raygne of Kynge Rychard the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no man ſhuld be ſo hardy to contriue, ſpeake, or tell any falſe newes, lyes, or other ſuche lyke falſe thinges of Prelates Dukes, Earles, Barons, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>there nobles &amp; Peares of the realme, or of the Chauncellour, Treſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, Clearke of the priuie ſeale, Steward of the kynge houſhold, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of the one bancke or of thother or of any other great officers of this realme. And that euery ſuch offendour ſhoulde be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned, vntil ſuch time, as he had brought him or them forth which did ſpeake the ſame. And wher alſo at a Parliament holden at Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge, in the .xxii. yeare of the raygne of the ſayde kynge Richard, it was alſo enacted, that where anye ſuche offendour as is aforeſayde ſhulde be taken and impriſoned, and coulde not fynde hym of whome he hearde thoſe newes, which he ſpake, as is aforeſayd, that then the ſame ſpeker ſhoulde be puniſhed by thaduice of the counſell, as by the ſame Actes amongeſt other more playnly doe and may appeare.</p>
            <p>Be it enacted by thauctoritie of this preſente Parliament, that all and euery the ſayde former Actes and Statutes ſhall be, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne in theyr full force ſtrength and effecte, to all intentes, conſtruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tions, and purpoſes. And further, that Iuſtices of the peace in euery Shire, citie, and towne corporate, within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> limittes of their ſeueral commiſſions, ſhall by aucthoritie of this preſent Acte, haue ful power to examine, heare, and determine the cauſes aboueſayd, in the ſayde two fyrſt Actes ſpecified, and to put the ſayd two fyrſt ſtatutes, and euery braunch in them conteyned in due execution that from hen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth condigne puniſhment be not defarred from ſuch offendour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as dyuerſe and ſondrye malicious and euill diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed perſons maliciouſly, ſediciouſiye, rebelliouſlye, and vnnaturally, contrary to the duitie of their fidilities and allegiaunces haue nowe of late not onely ymagined, inuented, pratized, ſpoken, and ſpredde abroad diuerſe and ſondry falſe, ſeditions, and ſlaunderous newes ru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mors, ſayinges, and tales, agaynſte our mooſte dreade Soueraygne Lord and Kyng, and agaynſt our moſt naturall Soueraygne La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye and Queene, and agaynſt eyther of them, of whom we are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to thinke euyll, and much more to ſpeake euyll, which offience ſoundeth, and is as well to the great diſhonour, reproche and ſclaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der of their moſte exellent maieſties, as alſo to the great ſclaunder of this their realme, and other their dominions, but alſo haue deuiſed, made, writen, prynted, publiſhed, and ſet forth diuerie haynous, ſedi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cious, and ſlaunderous writinges, rymes, ballades, letters, papers, and bookes, intending and practiſing therby to moue and ſtirre ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions, diſcord diſcention, &amp; rebellion within this realme, to the great
<pb facs="tcp:150877:5"/>peryll and daunger of the ſame.</p>
            <p>For auoydynge wherof, be it enacted by thaucthoritie of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parliament that yf any perſon or perſons, after the .xx. daye of February next enſuyng, and after open Proclamacion made of this Acte, ſhall maliciouſly, of his or theyr ymagination, ſpeake anye falſe ſedicious, &amp; ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derous newes, rumors, ſayinges, or tales of our ſayd Soueraigne Lord &amp; King, or of our ſayd moſt natural Soueraigne Lady &amp; Quene, that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al &amp; euery ſuch perſon and perſones ſo offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng, beyng therof conuicted or attaynted, in forme hereafter, in this Acte exprſſed, ſhall for euerye fyrſte offence, in ſome markette place, within the ſhyre, Citie or Borough, where, or neare vnto the place where the ſayde wordes were, or ſhalbe ſo ſpoken be ſet openly vpon the pylory, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sheriffe or his miniſters, if it ſhal fortune to be with out any citie or towne corporate. And if it happen to be within ſuche citie or towne corporate, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the principal officer or officers of ſuch citie or towne corporate or his or theyre miniſters, and there to haue bothe his eares cutte of, onleſſe he paye one hundreth poundes to the King and Quenes highnes vſe within one moneth next after iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment geuen of his ſayde offence, and alſo ſhall ſuffer impriſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ment by the ſpace, of three monethes, after ſuche his or theyr execution.</p>
            <p>And it is like wiſe enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayde, that al, and euery perſon &amp; perſones which after the ſayd daye, and after Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamacion made of this Acte, ſhall maliciouſly ſpeake any falſe, ſedici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and ſlaunderous newes, rumers, or tales, to the ſclaunder and reproche of our ſayd Soueraygne Lorde the Kynge, or of our ſayde mooſte naturall Soueraygne Lady the Queene, of the ſpeakynge or reportyng of any other, that then all, and euery ſuche perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo ſpeakyng and reportyng, being therof conuicte or atteynted, in forme hereafter, in this acte expreſſed, ſhall for euery ſuche offence in ſome market place within the ſhire, citie, borough, or towne, where or neare vnto the place, where the ſayd wordes were or ſhalbe ſo ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken &amp; reported, be ſet openly vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pillory by the ſhiriffe or his mini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſters, yf it ſhalfortune to be with out any citie or towne corporat. And yf it ſhall happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be within ſuche citie or towne corporate, then by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> principall officer or officers of ſuch citie or towne corporate, or his, or their miniſters, and ther to haue one of his eares cut of onleſſe he pay one hundred markes to the kinges &amp; Queenes highnes vſe, within one moneth next after iudgement geuen of his ſayde offence, and alſo ſhall ſuffer impriſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ment by the ſpace of one moneth after his or their executyon.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thauthritie aforeſayde, that yf anye perſon or perſones ſhall after the ſayde day and after Proclamation made as is aforeſayde, maliciouſly deuiſe, wryt, print, or ſet forth any maner of booke, ryme, ballade, lettre, or wrytyug, conteynynge anye
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:150877:5"/>falſe matter, clauſe, or ſentence of ſclaunder, reproche, and diſhonoure of the king &amp; Quenes maieſties, or of eyther of them, or to the encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragyng, ſturryng or mouyng of anye inſurrection or rebellion within this realme, or any the dominions belonging to the ſame. Or whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer ſhall maliciouſlye procure anye ſuche booke, ryme ballade, letter, or writing, to be writen, prynted, or ſet forth (and the ſayd offence not being puniſhable by the Statute, made in the .xxv. year of the raygne of king Edward the third, concerning treaſons, or declaration of trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon) that then, and in euerye ſuch caſe, the offender and offenders ther in after hys or their conuiction or attaynder, ſhall for his or theyr firſt offence, in ſome market place, within the ſhire, citie, or borough, where the ſayd offence, is, or ſhalbe committed or done, by the ſheriffe, or hys miniſters, yf it ſhall fortune to be wythoute anye citie, or towne corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and yf within ſuche citie or towne corporate, then by the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal officer, or officers of ſuch citie or town corporate, or by his or their miniſters, haue his and their right hande ſtryken of.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayde, that yf anye perſon or perſons, being once lawfullye conuicted of any of thoffences aforeſayde, nowe prouided to be puniſhed by the execution of loſſes of eare, eares, or hande, as is aforeſayd, do afterwardes, eftſones offend in anye of thoffences aforeſayde, that then he or they ſo offendynge, ſhall ſuffer impriſonment, durynge hys or theyr lyues, without bayle or maynpriſe, and forfeyte &amp; looſe to the king and Queenes maieſties al his and their goodes and cattelles.</p>
            <p>And it is alſo enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayde, that Iuſtices of oyer &amp; determiner, within the limittes of their commiſſion, Iuſtices of aſſiſe in their ſeuerall circuites, Iuſtices of gaole deliuery, and Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices of peace, as well within the liberties as without, within the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittes of their ſeuerall commiſſions, in their general ſeſſions, or other ſeſſions, which they or two of them whereof one of them to be of the <hi>Quorum</hi> maye, and ſhall appoynte at their pleaſure, where, and when nede ſhal require, &amp; ſhal by vertue hereof haue full power and auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to enquire, heare, and determine, all and euery thoffences afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd, as in caſes and triall of felonye. And that the partie indicted and arrayned, ſhal haue aduauntage of all maner of chalenges to the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye (peremptorye chalenge only excepte) as in triall of felonye.</p>
            <p>And alſo that euerye Iuſtice of peace within the limittes of his commiſſion ſhal haue ful power and aucthoritie to committe anye per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon, being vehementlye ſuſpected of any of the ſayd offences, toward, there co remayne without bayle or maynpriſe, vntyl he ſhalbe delyue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, accordyng to thys Acte.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayde, that no maner of perſon or perſons ſhalbe moleſted, or impeched for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye of thoffences, concernyng ſpeaking, or reportyng, as is aforeſaid,
<pb facs="tcp:150877:6"/>onleſſe he or they be thereof accuſed and conuicted within three mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethes, nexte after his or their ſayde offence ſo committed or done. And in caſe any perſon ſhalbe impriſoned for anye of the ſayde offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, concernyng ſpeakynge or reportinge, and not thereof conuicted, within three monethes, next after his offence ſuppoſed to be by hym done and committed, that then the perſon ſo impriſoned ſhalbe ſet at libertie, and no lenger deteyned in priſon.</p>
            <p>Prouided alſo, and be it enacted by aucthoritie aforeſayd, that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye ſuche Maiour, Maiours, Bayliffes, and other heade officer and officers of cities, boroughes, and townes corporate whiche haue, or hereafter ſhall haue iuriſditcion and aucthoritie, within the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall limittes of their office or offices, to hold and kepe ſeſſions, as Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice or Iuſtices of the peace ſhal, and may by aucthoritie hereof, as wel arreſt and committe to warde, al, &amp; euerye perſon and perſons, being vehemently ſuſpected of any of thoffences aforeſayde, as alſo to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede to thexecution, hearing, and determining of euery the ſaid offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, and to ſee, and make due execution thereof, according to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte, meanyng and effecte of this preſent Acte. Anye thynge in the ſame acte heretofore made to the contrarye notwythſtandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, that the ſayde Iuſtice of peace, as well within liberties as without, the which ſhall for anye the offences aforeſayd, committe anye perſon or perſons to warde, as is aforeſayd, ſhal with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in tenne dayes, next after ſuche committing, with one other Iuſtice, whereof one of them to be of the <hi>Quorum</hi> directe their precepte to the Shiriffe or Shiriffes of the countie, where thoffence ſhalbe commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or to other ordinary officer, yf it be within any citie, or towne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porate, where the Sheriffe can not intromytte, commaunding him or them by the ſame impanell and returne, as they ſhall aſſigne .xxiiij. good and lawful men of his or their baylywyke or baylywykes, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of the ſayde offence or offences the which anye ſuche perſon or perſons ſhalbe ſo impriſoned for. And therevpon within one moneth after the date of the ſayd precept, to procede and determine, as aboue is expreſſed. Euerye one of the ſame Iuſtices, vpon the payne of .x.li. to be payed to the king &amp; Queenes highneſſes, as often as they ſhalbe founden in defaulte of anye the ſame.</p>
            <p>Prouided alſo and be it enacted, that this Acte ſhalbe proclaymed in all the ſhyres within this realme, before the .xii. daye of Februarye next comming, to thintente that al perſons may haue notice thereof and auoyde the peryll and daunger that might enſue by offendynge agaynſt the ſame. And this Acte to be onlye in force, vntyl the ende of the next Parliament, and no longer.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayde, that none of the peares of this realme ſhalbe areſted or impriſoned for anye of the ſayde offences, but onely by order or commaundemente,
<pb n="vi" facs="tcp:150877:6"/>gyuen from the Kyngs and Quenes priuie counſayle, or of the heires of the Queene, and that the ſayde peares, and euery of them, that ſhal hereafter fortune to be indicted of any the offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces aforeſaid, ſhalbe tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed by their peares, as before hath ben accuſtomed in caces of treſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or fellonie.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An Acte for the punyſhment of certayne perſons callyng them ſelues Egyptians.</head>
            <head type="sub">¶ Te .iii. Chapter</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in a parliamente holden at Weſtminſter in the .xxii. yeare of the reigne of our late Soueraigne Lorde Kynge Henry theyght (for the auoyding and bauyſhinge oute of this realme of certayne outlandiſhe people, callinge them ſelues Egiptians, vſinge no crafte nor feare of marchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſes for to lyue by, but going fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> place to place, in great companies, vſing great, ſuttel, and craftye meanes, to diſceaue the kinges Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, bearing them in hand, that they by palmiſtry coulde tell mens and womans fortune, and ſo many tymes by crafte and ſubtiltie, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the people of thyre money, and committed diuers greate and heynous fellonies, and robberies, to the great hurt and diſceyt of the people). It was amongeſt other thinges then enacted that from the tyme of the makyng of the ſayd Acte, on ſuche perſonnes ſhoulde be ſuffered to come within this the kinges realme vpon payne of forfay ture to the kyng, all theyr goodes and catteles, and then to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to auoyde the realme within .xv dayes next after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement, vpon payne of impriſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ment, and ſuche perſons calling them ſelues Egiptians, as then were within this realme, ſhoulde departe within .xvi. dayes next after proclamation of the ſayde Acte vpon payne of impriſoment and forfeyture of all theyr goodes and cattels with diuers other clauſes &amp; articles conteyned in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd acte, as by the ſayd Act more at large it appeareth. Foraſmuche as diuers of the ſayde company, and ſuche otherlike perſones, not fearing the penaltie of the ſayd Statute, haue enterpriſed to come ouer agayne into this realme, vſyng theyr olde accuſtomed deueliſh, and noughty practiſes and deuiſes, with ſuche abhommable liuinge, as is not in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Chriſtian realme to be permitted, named, or knowen, and be not duely punyſhed for the ſame, to the perellous and euyl example of our ſoueraygne Lorde and Lady, the kynge and Queenes maieſties mooſt louinge ſubiectes, and to the vtter and extreame vndoynge of diuers and many of them, as euidently doth appeare.</p>
            <p>For reformation wherof, be it ordeyned and enacted by the kynge and Quene our ſoueraygne Lorde and Lady the Lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and commons in this preſent parliamente aſſembled and by thauctoritie of the ſame, that yf any perſon or perſons, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:150877:7"/>laſt daye of Ianuary next comming, do willingly tranſport, brynge, and conuey into this realme of England, or Wales, any ſuch perſons callyng them ſelues, or commonly called Egyptians, that then he or they, ſo tranſporting, bringinge, or conueying in, any ſuche perſons, contrary to the true meaning of this Acte, ſhall forfeyt and loſe for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery tyme ſo offendyng, forty poundes of lawfull money of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthoritie, aforeſayd that yf any of the ſayd perſons called Egyptians, whiche ſhalbe tranſported and conueyed into this realme of England or Wales, as is aforeſayd, do continue, and remayne within the ſame, by the ſpace of one moneth, that then he or they ſo offendyng, ſhall by vertue of this acte, be dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and adiudged a fellon, and fellons, and ſhall therefore ſuffer pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of death, loſſe of landes and goodes, as in caſes of fellony, by thor dre of the common lawe of this realme, and ſhall vpon the tryall of them, or any of them, therin be tried in the countie, and by thinhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauntes of the countie or place, where they or he ſhalbe apprehended or taken, and not <hi>Per medietanem linguae,</hi> and ſhal loſe the benefite and priui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege of ſanctuary and clergye.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thauctoritie aforſayd, that yf the Egyptians, and other perſons, commonly calling them ſelues Eyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, and euery of them, now beyng within this realme of Eugland, or Wales, do not departe out of the ſame within .xx. dayes next after proclamation of this preſente acte ſhalbe made, that then he or they which ſhall not departe within the ſayd tyme accordyng to the true meanyng of this Acte, ſhal forfeyt and loſe all his and theyr goodes and cattels, and that then it ſhalbe lawfull to all and euery the kynge and the Quenes ſubiectes, to ſeaſe the ſame, thone moytie thereof to be to the vſe of our ſoueraygne Lord &amp; Lady the kyng &amp; the Quene, and thother moytie therof to be the vſe of hym or them that ſhal, ſo ſeaſe the ſame.</p>
            <p>And be it alſo enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayd, that yf the Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, and other perſons commonly called Egyptians, and euerye of them, now beyng within this realme of Englande or Wales, do not departe out, and from the ſame within .xl. dayes next after proclama<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion ſhalbe made of this acte that then he or they, which ſhall not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, and auoyde within the ſayd time of .xl. dayes, accordyng to the true meaning of this acte, ſhalbe adiudged and deemed according to the lawes of this realme of England afellon, and fellons, and ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer therfore paynes of death. loſſe of landes and goodes, as in other caſes of felony, and ſhalbe tryed as is before ſaid, and without hauing any benefite or priuelege of Saynttuary or clergye.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayd, that yf anye perſon after the fyrſt day of Ianuarye next comming, ſhall ſue for the obteyninge of any lecence, lettre, or paſport, for anye of the ſayde per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:150877:7"/>called Egyptians, to abide or continue within this reamle of En<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glande or Wales, contrary to the tenour of this acte, that then euery ſuche perſone ſo ſuing, ſhall forfeyt and looſe for the ſame fortie poun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of lawefull money of England, and that euery ſuche licenſe, lettre &amp; paſport, ſhalbe by vertue of this acte voyde, to all intentes and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, thone moytie of all which ſummes of money to be forfayted, as is before ſayde, ſhalbe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kyng and Queene our ſoueraygne Lord and Lady, and thother moytie thereof to be hym or them, that will ſue for the ſame, in any courte of recorde, by accion of decte b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> plaint, or information, wherein any eſſoygne, wager of lawe, nor protection, ſhalbe admitted and allowed.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes and be it enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayde, that this preſent acte, nor any thinge therein conteyned, ſhall not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende, nor be hurtfull to any of the ſayde perſones, commonly called Egyptians whiche within the ſayde tyme of twenty dayes nexte af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſayde proclamation to be made, as in before ſayde, ſhall leaue that noughty ydle, and vngodly lyfe, and companie, and be placed in the ſeruice of ſome honeſte and able inhabitaunte or inhabitauntes, within this realme, or that ſhal honeſtly exerciſe him ſelfe in ſome law full worde or occupation, but that he or they ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuing in ſeruice or other lawful worke or occupatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhal duryng ſuch tyme as he or they ſhall ſo continue, be diſcharged of all paynes, and forfeytures, contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this acte.</p>
            <p>Prouided alſo, and be it enacted by the aucthoritie aforſayde, that this acte ſhall not in any wiſe extende to any chylde or chyldren, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng not aboue the age of .xiii. yeares, nor to any of the laid perſones, beyng nowe in priſon ſo that he or they ſo being in pryſone, do depart out of thys realme, within .xiiii. daies next after his or their diliuerie out of pryſon, nor ſhall extende to charge anyemaner of perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as acceſſary to any offence or offences, conteined or ſpecified in this eſtatute.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An acte to reſtrayne carriing of corne, victuals, and woodde ouer the ſea.</head>
            <head type="sub">¶ The .v. Chapter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here as ſundry goode eſtatutes and lawes hath bene made within this realme in the tyme of the Queenes highnes moſt noble progenitors, that none ſhuld tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte, carye or conueye out of this realme into anye place in the parties beyond the ſeas any corne, butter, cheeſe, or other victuall (except only for the vitailyng of the towne of Caleys, Hames, &amp; Guyſnes, and the marches of the
<pb facs="tcp:150877:8"/>ſame, vpon dyuerſe great paynes and forfeytures in the ſame contei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned, that notwithſtanding, many and ſondry couetous and vnſacia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble perſons, ſekyng their onely lucres and gaines, hath, and dayely doeth cary and conueigh innumerable quantitie, aſwel of corne, cheſe butter, and other victual, as of wood out of this realme, into the par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties beyond the ſeas. By reaſon whereof the ſayd corne, victual, &amp; wood, are growen vnto a wonderful dearth, and extreame prices, to the great detriment of the Common wealth of thys youre hyghnes realme, and your faythfull ſubiectes of the ſame.</p>
            <p>For remedie wherof, it may pleaſe your highnes that it maye bee enacted, and be it enacted by your highneſſe, by thaſſent of the lordes ſpiritual and temporall, and the commons in this preſent parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aſſembled, and by thauctoritie of the ſame, that no maner of perſon or perſones, after the .xx. day of Ianuary next comming ſhall cary and tranſport out of this realme by any Shippe, Craier, or other veſſel, whatſoeuer, into any place in the parties beyond the ſeas, or into the realme of Scotlande, any wheat, rie, barley, or other corne or grain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>growing within this realme, or any malte made wythin the ſame or any bere, butter, cheſe, herring or wood, except onely to and for the victualing and furniture of the townes of Calice, Hames, and Guiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and to the towne of Berwike and the marches of the ſame, with out ſufficient and lawfull aucthoritie ſo to do, vpon the paines &amp; pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties hereafter enſuing, that is to ſaye, thowner and owners of the ſayd ſhyppes and other veſſels, to forfeyte the ſaid ſhyppes, crayers, and other veſſels, with al their apparels, to them and euery of them belonging, wherein the ſayd corne, butter, cheſe, herring, byctuall, or wood, ſhalbe ſo tranſported and caried and the owners and owner of the ſayd corne, butter, cheſe, hearynge, and woode, to forfeyte the double value of the ſame, ſo caried and conueyed, and the mayſter &amp; mareners of euery of the ſayd ſhippes craiers, and veſſels, for eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuch offence, to forfeyte all theyr goodes, and to be impriſoned, by the ſpace of one whole yeare wythout bayle or maynpryſe.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayde, that yf any perſon or perſons, after the ſayd twenty day of Ianuary, do cary and conueye awaye by Bote, Crayer, or other veſſell, or otherwiſe anye wheat rye, barley, malte, or other corne or graine, or any beare, but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cheſe, herring or wood to anye Shippe or Veſſell, beyng on the Seas, or within any Hauen, creke, or other place of the border of this Realme to be tranſported, caried, and conueyed into any place in the parties beyond the Seas, or into the realme of Scotland, wythout ſufficient aucthoritie ſo to dooe, that then euery owner of the ſaid vi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctualles corne, and other thynges aboueſayde ſo tranſported or ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried and the owner and owners of euery ſuch bote or veſſell, and the botemen and mareners of the ſame ſhall looſe, forfeyte, and ſuffer all
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:150877:8"/>ſuch forfeytures, paynes, and penalties, as is aboue reherſed, thone moytie of all and euery which forfeyture or forfaytures, to be to the Kyng and Queenes hyghnes, theyr heyres and ſucceſſours, and tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther moytie to hym or them, that will ſue for the ſame by byl, informa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion, action of debte, or otherwiſe in any of the Kynge and Queenes hyghnes courtes of recorde, in whiche action, byl, or ſuit, the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunt ſhal not wage his lawe, nor haue any eſſoygne or protection to hym alowed.</p>
            <p>And be it enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayd, that yf any perſon or perſones ſhall optayne of the Kyng and Quenes maieſties, theyr hei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res or ſucceſſours, or of any of them, any licence to cary and tranſport any corne, victuall, or woode, into any partes beyond the ſeas, that if he or they, to whom any ſuche licence ſhalbe grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted, or any other, to whome ſuch perſon or perſons, hauing ſuch licence ſhall geue, graunt or fell his or theyr ſayd licence vnto, ſhall cary, and conuey, or cauſe to be carried and conueyed any more corne, victual or wood, then ſhalbe conteyned in his or their ſayd licence ſhal forfayt the triple value of the ſayd corne, victuall, or wood, ſo carried and tranſported, without ſufficient aucthoritie, and ſhal ſuffer impriſonment for one whole year in the common goale, where he ſhalbe apprehended, there to remaine without bayle or maynpryſe.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thauethoritie aforeſayd, that no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of perſon or perſones, after the ſayd .xx. day of Ianuary, that ſhal obteyne, or haue any ſuch licence for tranſporting and carying anye corne, victuall, or wood, into any parties beyond the ſeas, ſhall ſhippe, lade, and fraughte the ſame, or anye parte therof, at ſondrye places within this realme, but at one place certaine, vpon paine of forfeiture of the ſayd corne, victuall, &amp; wood, and al his goodes &amp; cattels, thone moytie thereof to the Kyng and Quenes maieſlies, theyr heyres &amp; ſucceſſours, and thother moytie to hym or them that wyll ſue for the ſame by action of debte, byll, playnt, information, or otherwyſe, wher in no wager of lawe, eſſoygne or protection ſhall be to hym or them allowed,</p>
            <p>And for the better execucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this acte, be it further enacted by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aucthoritie aforeſayd, that all and ſinguler Iuſtices of peace as well within the liberties as without, within theyr ſeuerall aucthorities &amp; commiſſions at any tyme, within thre yeares next after ſuche offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces committed, ſhal haue ful power and aucthoritie to enquire aſwel by the othes of twelue lawfull men, as alſo to heare and examine the mayſter, mayſters, and mareners of the ſaid ſhippes, craiers, &amp; other veſſels, and all, and euery other perſon and perſones, of all, and ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guler thoffenders againſt this preſent Acte, and to heare and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myne the ſame offences, as they maye, and ought to heare and deter mine any other treſſpaſſes, or offences.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150877:9"/>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it enacted by thauchoritie aforeſayde, that at all time and tymes hereafter, when the common price of corne within this realme is, that wheat ſhall not excede the price of .vi.s. viii.d. the quarter, &amp; tys. iiii.s. the quarter, &amp; barley .iii. ſhyllinges the quarter, it ſhalbe lawfull to euery perſon and perſones to cary &amp; tranſporte ouer the ſea to any place beyond the ſeas at their pleaſure of the ſayde kyndes of corne, ſo that it be not to the kyng and quenes enemies.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayd, that this Acte, ne any thing therin ronteyned, ſhall extende to anye perſon or perſons for the neceſſary victeling of any ſhippe, ſhippes, or other veſſels, but that they, and euery of them, may victayle the ſayd ſhyppes and veſſels, as they might haue done before the makyng of this preſent acte. This acte or any thing therein contayned to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayde, that this acte, or any thing therin conteyned, ſhal not be preiudiciall or hurtefull vnto the Lorde great Admirall of England, for the time beyng, or to the Kyng and Quenes maieſties iuriſdiction of the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miraltie, but that the ſayd Lord Admiral, or his deputie, or deputies maye and ſhall exerciſe, vſe, and execute al kynde of iuriſdiction, be longing to the ſea, according to his or their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſions, as they might lawfully haue done heretofore. This acte or any thing therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An Acte for the reuiuyng of three Eſtatutes made for the punyſhment of hereſies.</head>
            <head type="sub">¶ The .vi. Chapter</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the eſcheuing and auoyding of errours &amp; heriſies which of late haue ryſen, growen, and muche encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed within this realme, for that the Ordinaryes haue wanted auctoritie to procede agaynſt thoſe, that were infected therewith. Be it therefore ordeyned and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by the aucthoritie of this preſente parliamente, that the Statute made in the fift yere of the raigne of king Rychard the ſecond, concerning the arreſting and apprehenſion of erronious and hereticall preachers, and one other Statute, made in the ſecond yeare of the reygne of kyng Henry the fourth, concerning repreſſing of hereſies, and puniſhment of heretikes, and alſo one other Eſtatute made in the ſeconde yeare of the raygne of kynge Henrye the fyfte concernyng the ſupreſſion of hereſies and lollardrye, and euerye Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle, Braunche, and ſentence conteygned in the ſame three ſeuerall
<pb n="ix" facs="tcp:150877:9"/>Actes, and euery of them, ſhall fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the twenty day of Ianuary nexte commyng, be reuiued, and be in full force, ſtrength, and effecte, to all intentes, conſtructions and purpoſes for euer.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="statute">
                        <head>¶ The tenor of the fyrſte acte, made in the fyfth yeare of kynge Rycharde, is as foloweth. Chap. v.</head>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Tem, foraſmuche as it is openly knowen, that there be diueres euil perſones within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> realme, going from countie to countie, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> toune to toune, in certain habites, vnderdiſſimulacion of greate holines, &amp; with out the licence of the Ordinaries of the places, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſufficient aucthoritye, preachynge dayly, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye in Churches &amp; Churcheyardes, but alſo in mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kettes, Fayres, &amp; other ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> places, where a greate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple is, dyuers Sermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyninge hereſies, &amp; not or yous errours, to the greate embleamiſhyng of the chriſten fayth, and deſtruction of the Lawes, and of the eſtate of holy Churche, to the greate pericle of the ſoules of the people, and of all the realme of England, as more playn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is found, and ſufficiently proued, before the reuerend father in God the Archebyſhop of Canterbury, and the Byſhopes, andother prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, maſters of diuinitie, and doctours of Canon and of Cyuil, and a great parte of the clergye of the ſayd realme: eſpecially aſſembled for this cauſe: which perſones do alſo preach dyuers, matters of ſiaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, to engender diſcorde and diſcention betwixt diuers eſtates of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd realme: aſwell ſpirituall, as temporal, in exciting of the people, to the great peryll of all the Realme, which preachers cited or ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned before the Ordinaries of the places, there to aunſwer of that wherof they be impeched, wyll not obey to theyr ſummons and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes, nor care not for theyr monicions nor ſenſures of the hole churche, but expreſſely deſpice them: And more ouer, by their ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyl and ingeneous wordes, do drawe the people to here their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mones, and do maintayn them in their errours by ſtronge, hand by greate coutes: It is ordeined and aſſented in this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Parliament that the kinges commiſſions be made and directed to the Sheriffes and other miniſters of our ſoueraygne Lorde the kyng, or other ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient perſones learned, and accordyng to the certificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lates therof to be made in the Chauncerie, from tyme to tyme, to ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſt al ſuch preachers, and alſo theyr fautours, mainteiners, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bettours, and to holde them in arreſt and ſtrong pryſon, tyll they wil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iuſtifie them according to the lawe and reaſon of holy Churche. And the kyng wyll and commaundeth, that the Chauncelloure make ſuch comiſſions at all tymes, that he by the prelates, or any of them ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be certefied, and therof requyred, as is aforeſayde.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="statute">
                        <pb facs="tcp:150877:10"/>
                        <head>¶ The tenor of the ſeconde acte, made in the ſeconde yeare of kynge Henry the .iiii. is as foloweth. Cap. xv.</head>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Tem wher as it is ſhewed to our ſoueraigne Lord the Kynge, on the behalfe of the prelates and Cleargye of his realme of Englande in this preſent Parliamente, that although the catholike faith builded vpon Chriſt and by his Apoſtles, and the holy churche ſufficientlye determined, declared and approued, hath bene hether to by good and holy, and moſt noble progenitours of our ſoueraigne Lorde the kyng in the ſayd Realme, emongeſt all the realmes of the worlde, moſte deuoutly obſerued, and the Churche of Englande, by his ſayd moſt noble progenitours and aunceſtours, to the honour of God, and the whole realme aforeſayde, laudably endowed, and in her rightes and liberties ſuſteined, without that that the ſame faith, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Churche was hrute or greuouſly oppreſſed, or els perturbed by any peruers doctrine, or wicked heretical or erronious opinions: yet neuertheleſſe, diuers falſe and peruerſe people, of a certayne new ſect of the faithe of the Sacramentes of the Churche, and the aucthoritie of the ſame, damnably thinkyng, and agaynſt the lawe of God and of the church, vſurpyng the office of preaching, do peruerſly and mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly, in diuers places within the ſayd realme, vnder the coloure of diſſimuled holineſſe, preache and teache theſe daies ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly and preuely diuers new doctrines, and wicked hereticall and erronious opimo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s contrary to the ſame fayth, and bleſſed determinations of the holye Churche. And of ſuch ſecte and wicked doctryne and opinions they make vnlawfull conuenticles, and confederaties, they hold and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe ſcholes, they make and wryte bokes, thei do wickedly inſtructe &amp; infourme people, and aſmuche as they maye, excite and ſtirre them to ſedition and inſurrection, and maketh great ſtrife and diuiſion emo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge the people, and other enormities horrible to be harde dayly doo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrate and commit, in ſubuercion of the ſayd catholike faith, and do etryne of the holy churche, in diminution of Gods honour and alſo in deſtruction of the eſtate, rightes, and liberties of the ſayd churche of Englande, by whiche ſecte and wicked and falſe preachynges, doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and opinions of the ſayd falſe and peruerſe people, not only moſt greateſt peryll of the ſoules, but alſo many more other hurtes ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and perilles (which God prohibite) might come to this realme onleſſe it be the more ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifully and ſpedely holden by the kynges ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie in this behalf, namely where as the dioceſans of the ſaid realme cannot by their iuriſdiction ſpiritual, without aide of the ſayde royall Maieſtie, ſufficiently correct the ſayde falſe and peruerſe people, nor refrayn theyr malice, becauſe the ſayd falſe and peruerſe people do go from Dioces to Dioces, and wyl not appeare before the ſayd Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſans, but the ſame Dioceſans, and their iuriſdiction ſpiritual, and the
<pb n="vii" facs="tcp:150877:10"/>kayes of the churche, with the cenſures of the ſame, doo vtterly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempne and deſpiſe, and ſo theyr wicked preachinges and doctrines, dooeth from day to day continue and execiſe, to the hatred of right and reaſon, and vtter deſtruction ordre and good rule. Vpon which nowelties and exceſſes aboue reherſed. The Prelates and clergie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forſayde, and alſo the commons of theſayde realme, beyng in the ſame parliament, praing our ſoueraine Lorde the king, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> his roial highnes woulde vouchſafe in the ſayde parliamente, to prouide a conneunient remedie, the ſame our ſoueraigne Lordethe kyng, gratiouſly conſide ryng the premiſſes, and alſo the laudable ſteppes of his ſayd moſte no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble progenitours and aunceſters, for the conſeruation of the ſayd ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholyke fayth, and ſuſtentation of Goddes honour, and alſo the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde of the eſtate, rightes, and liberties of the ſayd Churche of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glande, to the laude of God, and merite of our ſayd ſoueraygne lorde the kynge, and proſperitie &amp; honour of all his ſayd realme, and for the eſchewing of ſuche diſſentions, diuiſions, hurtes, ſlaunders, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riles, in tyme to come, and that this wicked ſecte, preachinges, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and opinions, ſhould from henceforth ceaſe, and be vtterlye deſtroied, by thaſſent of the ſtates, &amp; other diſcrete men of the realme beyng in the ſayd parliament, hath graunted, ſtabliſhed, and ordeined fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence forth, fermly to be obſerued, that none within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde realme or any other dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſubiectes to his roial maieſtie, preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e to prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che openly or priuely, without the licence of the Dioceſan of the ſame place, fyrſt required and obteined, curates in their owne churches, &amp; perſones he therto priuileged, and other of the canon lawe graunted, onely excepte. Nor that none from henceforth anye thynge preache, hold teache, or inſtruct, openly or priuely, or make or write any boke, contrary to the catholyke fayth or determination of the holy church nor of ſuche ſect and wicked doctrines and opinions, ſhal make anye conuenticles, or in any wyſe hold or exerciſe Scholes. And alſo that none from henceforth in anye wiſe fauoure ſuche preacher, or maker of anye ſuche, &amp; lyke conuenticles, or holdyng or exercſynge ſcholes, or makyng, or writing ſuch bookes, or ſo teachynge, infourminge, or exciting the people nor any of the in maintain, or in any wiſe ſuſteine. And that all, and ſinguler hauyng ſuche bookes or any wrytinges of ſuch wicked doctrine and opinions, ſhall really with effect deliuer, or cauſe to be deliuered all ſuch bokes &amp; writinges to the Dioceſan of the ſame place, within .xl. dayes from the tyme of the proclamatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this ordinaunce &amp; ſtatute. And if any perſon or perſons, of whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer kynde, eſtate, or condition that he or they be, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> henceforth do, or acce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt againſt the royall ordinaunce &amp; ſtatute aforeſaide in the premiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes or in any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or ſuche bokes in the fourme aforeſayd, do not deli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer, then the dioceſan of the ſame place in his dioces ſuche perſon or perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es in this be balfe defamed, or euidently ſuſpected, &amp; eueri of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <pb facs="tcp:150877:11"/>may by the aucthoritie of the ſayd ordinarie and Statute, cauſe to be arreſted, and vnder ſaufe cuſtody in his priſones to be deteined, til he or they of the articles layed to hym or them in this behalfe, do canoni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cally purge him or them ſelfe, or els ſuch wicked ſecte, preachynges, doctrynes, and heretical and, erronious opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, do abiure, according as the lawes of the churche doth require, ſo that the ſayd dioceſan by him ſelf, or his commiſſaries, do openly and iudicially procede againſt ſuch perſones ſo arreſted, and remayning vnder his ſauſe cuſtody to all effecte of the lawe, and determin that ſame buſineſſe, according to the Canonicall decrees, wythin three monethes after the ſayd arreſt any laweful impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ceaſſing. And yf any perſon in any caſe aboue expreſſed, be before the dioceſan of that place, or his commiſſaries ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonically conuicte, then the ſame dioceſan may do to be kept in his pri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon the ſayd perſon ſo conuicte, for the maner of his defaut, and after the qualitie of the offence, according and as long as to his diſcretion ſhal ſeme expediente, and moreouer to put the ſame perſon to the ſecu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lar court, except in caſes where he according to the canonical decret ought to be left, to pay to our ſoueraygne lord the kyng, his pecunier fine, according as the ſame fine ſhall ſeme competent to the dioceſan, for the maner and qualitie of the offence, in whiche caſe the ſame dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſan, ſhalbe bound to certifye the kynge of the ſame fine in his eſchec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ker, by his Lettre Patentes, ſealed with his ſeale, to the effect that ſuch fine by the kynges aucthoritie, maye bee required and leuied to his vſe of the goodes of the ſame perſon ſo conuict. And if any perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> within the ſayd realme and dominions, vpon the ſayd wycked prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chynges, doctrynes, opinions, ſchooles, and heretical and erronious informations, or any of them be before the dioceſan of the ſame place, or his commiſſaries ſencencially conuicte &amp; the ſame wicked ſect, prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chinges, doctrines and opinions, ſcholes, &amp; informations, doe refuſe duely to abiure, or by the dioceſan of the ſame place or his commiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries after the abiuration made by the ſame perſon pronounced, fal in to relapſe, ſo that according to the holy canons, he ought to be left to the ſeculer court, whervpon credence ſhalbe geuen to the dioceſan of the ſame place, or to his comiſſaries in thys behalfe, then the ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe of the countie of the ſame place, and Maior and ſheriffes or ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe, or Maior and Bayliffes of the citie, towne, and borough of the ſame countie next to the ſame dioceſan, or the ſayde Commyſſaryes, ſhalbe perſonally preſent in preferring of ſuch ſentences, when they by the ſame dioceſan or his commiſſaries ſhalbe required: &amp; they the ſame perſones and euery of them, after ſuche ſentence promulgate, ſhall receaue: and them before the people in an high place dooe to be brent, that ſuche punyſhment maye ſtrike in feare to the myndes of other, wherby no ſuch wicked doctrine and hereticail, and erronious opinions, nor their abbettours and fautours in the ſayd realme &amp; do
<pb n="xv" facs="tcp:150877:11"/>minions agaynſt the catholike fayth, chriſten lawe and determinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the holy church (which God prohibite) be ſuſteyned, or in any wyſe ſuffered, in which al, and ſinguler the premiſſes, concerning the ſayde ordinaunce and ſtatute, the ſheriffes, maiors, and baylyffes, of the ſaid counties, cities, boroughes, and townes, ſhalbe attending, ayding, &amp; ſupporting, to the ſayde dioceſans and their commiſſaries.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="statute">
                        <head>¶ The tenor of the third Acte, made in the ſeconde yeare of kyng Henry the fyft, is as foloweth. Cap. vii.</head>
                        <p>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Tem foraſmuche as great rumours, congregations, &amp; in ſurrections, here in the realme of England by dyuerſe of the kinges liege people, as wel by them whiche were of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſect of hereſies commonly called lollardrie, as by other of their confederacie, excitation, &amp; abbetment, nowe of late were made, to the intent to adnull, deſtroye, and ſubuerte the chriſten faythe, and the lawe of God and holy churche within thys ſame realme of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, &amp; alſo to deſtroye, the ſame our ſoueraygne lorde the kyng, &amp; all other maner of eſtates of the ſame realme of Englande as wel ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>all as temporall, and alſo all maner of policie and finally the lawes of the lande: The ſame our ſoueraygne lord the kyng, to the honour of god, and in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſeruation &amp; fortification of the chriſten fayth, and alſo in ſaluation of his royall eſtate, and of the eſtate of al his realme, willing agaynſt the malice of ſuch heretikes and lollardes to prouide a more open remedy and puniſhment then hath bene had and vſed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> caſe heretofore, ſo that for feare of the ſame lawes and punyſhmente, ſuch heriſtes and lollardries may the rather ceaſe in tyme to come, by the aduiſe and aſſent aforeſaid, and at the prayer of the ſayd co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons, hath ordeyned and ſtabliſhed: that fyrſt the chaunceler, treaſurer, Iuſtices of the one bench and of the other, Iuſtices of peace, ſheriffes, maiors, and baylyffes of cities and townes, and al other officers, hauing go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernaunce of people, which nowe be, or hereafter for the tyme ſhalbe, ſhal make an othe in takyng of their charges and occupations, to put their whole power &amp; diligence, to put out and do to be put out, ceaſe, &amp; deſtroye al maner of hereſies and errours, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly called lollardries within the places where they exerciſe their offices &amp; occupatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tyme to tyme with all their power, &amp; that they aſſiſte the ordinaries, and their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſaries &amp; them fauour &amp; maintayne as often as they or any of them to that ſhalbe required by the ſame ordinaries or their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſaries, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> when the ſaid officers &amp; miniſters trauayle or ride to arreſt any lollard, or to make aſſiſtence at the inſtaunce &amp; requeſt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordinaries or their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſaries bi vertne of this ſtatute, that the ſame ordinaries &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſaries ſhall pay for their coſtes reaſonablye. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the kynges ſeruices, to the whych the ſame officers be firſt ſworne, be
<pb facs="tcp:150877:12"/>preferred before all other ſtatutes for the libertie of holy church &amp; the miniſters of the ſame, and in eſpeciall for the correction &amp; puniſhment of the heretikes and lollardes before this time made and not repelled being in their force. And alſo that al perſons co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uict of hereſie, of what eſtate, condition, or degre that they be, by the ſaid ordinaries or other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſaries left to the ſeculer power, according to the lawes of holye churche, ſhal looſe and forfayt al theyr landes and tenementes, which they haue in fee ſymple in the maner as foloweth, that is to ſaye, that the king haue all the landes &amp; tenementes, which the ſayd conuictes haue in fee ſimple &amp; holden of him immediatly as forfayte, &amp; that the o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther lordes, of whome the landes &amp; tenementes of ſuch conuictes be bolden immediatly, after that the kyng is ſo ſeaced &amp; aunſwered of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yeare the day, and the waſt, haue liuery out of the kynges handes of the landes &amp; teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes aforeſaid of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo holden, as it hath bene vſed in the caſe of attainder of felonie, except y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> landes &amp; tenementes, which be holden of the ordinaries or their commiſſaries, before whome any ſuch perſons impeched of hereſie be conuict, which landes &amp; teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, intierly ſhall remayne to the kyng as forfayte. And moreouer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goodes &amp; cattels of theſe perſons ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uicted, be forfaytto our ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raygne lord the kyng, ſo that no perſon conuict of hereſy, &amp; left to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer power after the lawes of holy church, ſhal forfait his landes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he be dead. And yf any ſuch perſon ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uict, be enfeffed be it by fyne by dede, or without dede, in la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des or teneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, rentes, or ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices, in fee or otherwiſe, or hath any other poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or cattels bi gift or grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of any perſon or perſons to anothers vſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of ſuch conuictes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame landes nor tenementes, rentes nor ſeruices, nor ſuch other poſſeſſions, nor cattels ſhalbe forfeyt to our ſoueraigne lord the king in no wiſe. And moreouer y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the iuſtices of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinges benche, &amp; iuſtices of peace, &amp; iuſtices of aſſiſe, haue ful power to enquire of al the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which hold any errors or hereſies, as lollardes, &amp; which be their main temers, receyuers, fauorers &amp; ſuſtemers, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men writers of ſuch boo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes as wel of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſermons, as of their ſcholes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenticles, congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and confederacies. And that this clauſe be put in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſions of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peace. And yf any perſons be endicted of ani pointes aforeſaid the ſayd Iuſtices ſhal haue power to award againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Capias, and the ſheriffe ſhalbe bound to arreſt the perſon or perſons ſo endicted as ſone as he may them find by hym or by his officers. And foraſmuch as the congniſaunce of hereſie, errours &amp; lollardries, belongeth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of holy church, and not to the ſeculer iudges ſuch perſons endic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſhalbe delyuered to the ordinaries of the places or to their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ries, by indentures bytwyxt them to be made, within .x. daies after theyr arreſt, or ſoner yf it may be, thereof to be acquyte or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uict by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawes of holy church, in caſe that theſe perſones be not endicted of an other thing, wherof the cogniſaunce belongeth to the ſeculer iudges
<pb n="xii" facs="tcp:150877:12"/>and officers, in whiche caſe, after that, that they be acquyte or dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered before the ſeculer Iudges of ſuch thinges to the ſeculer Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges belongyng, they ſhalbe ſent in ſafegard to the ſayde ordynary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, or to theyr commiſſaries, and to them deliuered by indentures, as before to be acquyte or conuicte of ſuch lollardryes, errours, or here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, as is aforeſayd, after the lawes of holy churche, and that within the terme aforeſayd.</p>
                        <p>Prouided alwayes that the ſayde endictementes be not taken in euydence but for information before the ſpirituall iudges agaynſte ſuche perſones ſo endicted, but that the ordinaries commence theyr proceſſe agaynſt ſuch perſons endicted in the ſame maner as though no endictement were, hauing no regarde to ſuch endictmentes. And yf anye be endicted of hereſie, erroure, or lollardrye, and taken by the Sheriffe or other officer, he ſhalbe lette to mayne pryſe within the ſayd tenne dayes by good ſuertie for whome the ſayd Sheriffes or other officers will aunſwere, ſo that the ſayd perſon or perſones, whiche were ſo endicted, be ready to be deliuered to the ſayde ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries, or to theyr commiſſaries, before the ende of the ſayde tenne dayes, yf he may by any meanes for ſyckenes. And euery ordinarye ſhall haue ſufficient commiſſaries, or commiſſarye dwelling in euery countie in a place notable, ſo that yf any ſuch perſon ſo endicted be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, that the ſayde commiſſaries, or commiſſarye maye be warned in the notable place where he dwelleth, by the Sheriffe, or ſome of hys officers, to come to the kynges iayle in the ſame countie, there to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue the ſame perſon ſo endicted by indentures as before. And that in the enqueſt in this caſe to be taken, the Sheriffes and other offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, to whome it belongeth ſhall do to be empanelled good and ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient perſons, not ſuſpected nor procured, that is to ſay, that euery of them whiche ſhalbe ſo empanelled in ſuch enqueſte, haue wythin the realme of Englande. C. s. of landes, tenementes, or of rent by yeare, vpon payne to loſe to the bynges vſe .x.li. and they which ſhalbe em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>panelled in ſuch enqueſtes in Wales, euery of them ſhall haue to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lue of .xl. s. by yeare. And yf any ſuch perſon be areſted, be it by the ordinarie, or by the kynges officers or miniſters, &amp; eſcape or breake y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pryſon, before that he be acquite before the ordinary, the goodes and cattels, whiche he hadde the daye of ſuche arreſte, ſhalbe forfeyre to the kynge and his landes and tenementes, which he hadde the ſame daye, ſeaſed alſo into the kynges handes, the kyng ſhall haue the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fytes thereof from the ſayde day, vntil he be yelded to the priſon from which he eſcaped. And that the forſayd Iuſtices haue full power to enquyre of al ſuch eſcapes, breakyng of pryſon, and alſo of landes and tenementes, goodes and catteles of ſuch perſones ſo endicted.</p>
                        <p>Prouided alſo that yf any ſuch perſon endicted do not retourne to the ſayd pryſon and dyeth not conuicte it ſhalbe lawfull to his heires
<pb facs="tcp:150877:13"/>to entre into the landes and tenementes of theyr aunceſtre, wythout anye other purſuyte makyng to the kynge for thys cauſe, and then al they whych haue liberties and fraunchiſes royall in Englande, as in the countie of Cheſter, the countie and libertie of Durham, and other lyke, and alſo al the Lordes, which haue iuriſdiction and fraunchiſes royall in Wales, wher the kynges writtes do not runne, haue power to execute and put in due execution theſe articles, in al poyntes by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or by theyr officers, in lyke maner as the Iuſtices and other the kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges officers before declared ſhoulde do.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An acte that perſons dwellyng in the countrye, ſhall not ſel diuers wares in cities, or townes corporate by retayle.</head>
            <head type="sub">¶ The .vii. Chapter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here before thys tyme the auncient cities, boroughes, Townes corporate, &amp; markette townes within this realme of Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, haue bene verye populous, &amp; chief<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly inhabited with marchauntes, artificers, &amp; handye craftes men duryng which tyme the chyldren in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd cities, boroughes, towe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s corporate, &amp; market townes were ciuilye brought vp, and inſtructed, and alſo the ſayde cities, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughes, and townes corporate kept in good ordre and obeyſaunce, and the inhabiters of the ſame wel ſet on worke, and kept from ydle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. By reaſon whereof, the ſayde cities, boroughes, and townes cor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>porate, did then proſper in riches, and great welth, and were as then not onely able to ſerue and furnyſh the kyng and Queenes maieſties, and other theyr noble progenitours, kynges of this realme, aſwel with great numbers of good able perſones, and well furny ſhed mete for the warres, as alſo then charged 'and yet chargeable, with great fee farmes, quyndemes, taxes, and dyuers other paymentes to the kynge and Queenes maieſties, whiche at this preſent they be not able to pay and beare, but to theyr vtter vndoyng, beyng fewe in number to pay and beare the ſame, but alſo the ſame cities, bouroughes, and townes corporate, are lyke to come very ſhortly to vtter deſtruction, ruyne, and decay, by reaſon wherof the occupiers, lynnen, draperes, wollen drapers, haberdaſhars, and Grocers, dwellinge in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes out of the ſaid cities, boroughes, townes corporate, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket townes, do not onely occupye the arte and miſtery of the ſayde ſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ences, in the places where they dwel and inhabite, but alſo come vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſayd cities, boroughes townes corporate and market townes and there ſel theyr wares, and take awaye the relief of the inhabitau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of the ſayd cities, boroughes, townes corporate, and market tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to the great decay, and vtter vndoynge of the inhabitauntes of
<pb n="xiii" facs="tcp:150877:13"/>the ſame, yf ſpedy reformation therein, be not had in tyme conuenie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t For remedie whereof, and for the better amendement of the ſayde ci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties boroughes, townes corporate, and market townes, and to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the ſame cities, boroughes, and townes corporate, may be the better able to pay the ſayd fee fermes, and alſo to beare the other ordynary charges within the ſame cities, boroughes, and townes corporate, and to furnyſhe the kyng and Quenes maieſties, which numbers of able perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, like as they heretofore haue done in times paſt, in times of warre.</p>
            <p>Be it therefore enacted by our ſoueraygne Lorde and Ladye, the kyng and Queene, the lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in this preſent parliament aſſembled, and by auctoritie of the ſame, that any perſon or perſones, which do nowe inhabite &amp; dwell, or hereafter ſhall inhabite or dwell in the country any where or coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty wythin this realme of England, out of any of the ſayde cities, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughes, townes corporate, or market townes, from, and after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feaſt of S. Michael tharchaungel next comming, ſhall not ſell or cauſe to be ſold by retayle, any wollen cloth, linnen cloth, haberdaſhe wares Grocery wares, mercery wares, at, or within any of the ſaid cities, boroughes, townes corporate, or market townes, or w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in the ſuburbs or liberties of the ſayd cities boroughes, townes corporate, &amp; mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket townes, wythin this ſaid realme of England (except it be in open fayres) vpon payne to forfeyt and looſe for euery tyme ſo offending y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſumme of vi. s. viii. d. and the hole wares ſo ſolde, proferred, and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to be ſolde, contrary to the forme, intente, and effect of thys pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent acte, as aboue is ſayd, the one moytie of all which forfaytures, to be to the vſe of our ſayd ſoueraygne Lorde and Lady the kyng and Queenes maieſties, and the other halfe to him or them that ſhal ſeaſe and ſewe for the ſame in any of the kyng and queenes courtes of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, by byll, playnt, action of debte, informacion or otherwiſe, wher in no eſſoigne, protection or, wager of lawe, ſhalbe alowed.</p>
            <p>Prouided alway, that this acte ſhall not in any wyſe extende, nor be hurtefull to any perſon or perſons, that bring any of the ſayde wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len cloth, lynnen cloth, haberdaſh, Grocery, mercery ware or wars, to anye of the ſayd cities, boroughes, townes corporate, or markette townes to be ſolde, or cauſe to be ſolde by whole ſale, in groſſe, and not byretayle, but they and euery of them may laufully ſell the ſame, in as large and ample maner, forme and, condition by whole ſale in groſſe, &amp; not by retayle, as they and euery of them, myght haue done at any tyme or tymes before the makyng of this act. Any thing here in to the contrary, notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alway, that this preſent acte ſhall not extende to anye perſon or perſons, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nowe dwel or inhabit in the country, or hereafter
<pb facs="tcp:150877:14"/>ſhall dwell or inhabite out of any of the ſaid cities, boroughes, towns corporate, or market townes, but that they, and euerye of them at any tyme hereafter, when they, or any of them ſhalbe free of anye the guyldes, &amp; liberties of any the ſayd cities, boroughes, townes corpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rate, or market townes, and dwel or inhabite within any of the ſame cities, boroughes, townes corporate, or markette townes, that they and euery of them ſo being free, ſhall and may ſel or cauſe to be ſolde, any of the wares aforeſayd, by retayle, in as ample and large maner as they, and euery of them, might haue done, beinge free of the ſayde cities, boroughes, and townes aforeſayd, before the makyng of thys Acte. Any clauſe or article in this acte to the contrarye notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge.</p>
            <p>Prouyded alwayes, and be it enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayd that it ſhalbe lawefull to all perſones, to ſell or cauſe to be ſold by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayle or otherwiſe, al maner of cloth, lynnen, or wollen, of theyr owne makyng, in euery citie, borough, towne corporate, and market towne within this realme, as freely and franckly as they might haue done before the makyng of this Acte Anye thynge in the ſame conteyned to the contrary hereof notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alway, that this acte, or any thing therein conteyned, ſhall not be preiudiciall or hurtefull to the liberties, and priuileges of the vniuerſities of Cambrydge and Oxforde, or eyther of them, Any thing in thys Acte heretofore mentioned to the contrary notwyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An Acte repealyng all Statutes, articles, and prouiſions, made Agaynſt the Sea Apoſtolyke of Rome, ſynce the .xx. yeare of Kynge Henry the eyght, and alſo for theſtablyſhment of all ſpirytuall and eccleſiaſticall poſſeſſions, and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditamentes conueyed to the laytie.</head>
            <head type="sub">¶ The .viii. Chapter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here as ſynce the .xx. yeare of Kynge Henry theight of famous memory, father vnto youre maieſtie, oure moſt naturall ſoueraygne, and gratious Ladye and Queene, muche faiſe and erronious doctryne, hathe bene taught, preached, and written partly by dyuers, the naturall borne Subiectes of this realme &amp; parte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye beyng brought in hether from ſondry other forreyne countryes, hath bene ſowen and ſpred abroad within the ſame. By reaſon wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of aſwel the ſpiritualtie as the temporaltie of your highnes realmes and dominions, haue ſwerued from the obedience of the Sea Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyke, and declined from the vnitie of Chriſtes churche, and ſo haue
<pb n="xiiii" facs="tcp:150877:14"/>continued, vntyl ſuche tyme as your maieſtie beynge fyrſt reyſed vp by God, and ſet in the ſeat Royal ouer vs, and then by his diuine and gratious prouidence knyt in marriage with the mooſt noble &amp; ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Prynce, the kynge our ſoueraygne Lorde your huſbande, the Popes holynes, and the Sea Apoſtolike, ſent hither vnto your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties (as vnto perſones vndefiled, and by Gods goodnes preſerued from the common infection aforeſayde) and to the whole realme, the mooſt reuerend father in God the Lorde Cardinall Poole Legate, <hi>de latere</hi> to call vs home agayne into the right waye, frome whence we haue al this long while wandered, and ſtrayed abrode. And we after ſondrye longe, and, greuous plagues, and calamities, ſeinge by the goodnes of god our owne errours, haue acknowledged the ſame vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſayde mooſte reuerende father, and by hym haue bene, and are the rather at the contemplation of your maieſties, receyued and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced into the vnitie and boſome of Chriſtes churche, and vpon our humble ſubmiſſion &amp; promiſſe made for a declaration of our repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce to repeale and aborgate ſuch actes and Statutes as had bene made in parliament, ſynce the ſayd .xx. yeare of the ſayde kynge Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry theyght, agaynſt the ſupremacy of the Sea Apoſtolike, as in oure ſubmiſſion exhibited to the ſayde moſte reuerende father in God, by your maieſties appeareth. The tenor wherof enſueth</p>
            <p>We the Lordes ſpirituall, and temporall, and the commons aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in this preſent parliament, repreſentynge the whole body of the realme of Englande, and the dominions of the ſame, in the name of our ſelues perticulerlye and alſo of the ſayde body vniuerſally in this our ſupplication, directed to your maieſties with mooſt humbly ſuit that it may by your graces interceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and meane be exhibited to the mooſte reuerend father in God, the Lorde Cardinall Poole legate, ſent ſpeciallye hyther from our mooſte holye father Pope Iulye the thyrd, and the Sea Apoſtolike of Rome, do declare our ſelues very ſorye and repentaunte, of the ſciſme and diſobedience, committed in this realme and dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s aforeſayd agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd Sea Apoſtolike, eyther by makyng, agreing, or execting any lawes, ordinaunces, or commaundementes, agaynſt the ſupremacy of the ſaid Sea, or other wyſe doyng or ſpeakyng, that myght impugne the ſame: offerynge our ſelues, and promiſyng by this our ſupplication, that for a token &amp; knoweledge of our ſayd repentaunce, we be and ſhalbe alwayes ready vnder, and with thauctorities of our miaeſties, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vttermooſte of our powers, to do that ſhall lye in vs, for the abrogation and repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge of the ſayde lawes and ordinances in this preſent parliament, aſwell for our ſelues as for the whole bodye, whome we repreſente, where vpon we mooſt humbly deſyre your maieſties, as perſonages vndefiled in thoffence of hys body towardes the ſayde Sea, whiche neuertheleſſe God by his prouydence, hath made ſubiect to you, ſo to
<pb facs="tcp:150877:15"/>ſet forth this our mooſte humble ſuite, that we maye obtayne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Sea Apoſtolyke, by the ſayde mooſt reuerend father, aſwell perticu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lerlye, as generally, abſolution, releaſe, and diſcharge, from all daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of ſuche cenſures, and ſentences, as by the lawes of the churche we be fallen into. And that we maye as children repentaunt, be recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the boſome and vnytye of Chriſtes churche, ſo as this noble realme, with all the members therof, maye in this vnitie, and perfect obedience to the Sea Apoſtolike, and Popes, for the tyme beynge, ſerue God and your maieſties, to the furtheraunce and aduaunceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his honour and glory. We are at the interceſſion of your maieſties, by thaucthoritie of our holy father, Pope Iuly the thyrde, and of the Sea Apoſtolike, aſſoyled, diſcharged, and deliuered from excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, interdictions and other cenſures Eccleſiaſticall which hath hanged ouer our heades for our ſayde defaultes, ſynce the tyme of the ſayd ſciſme, mentioned in our ſupplication. The whiche tyme the ſayd Lorde Legate, and we, do al declare, recogniſe, and meane by this acte, to be onely ſynce the .xx. yeare of the raygne of our moſt noble father, Kyng Henry theyght. It maye nowe lyke your maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties, that for the accomplyſhment of our promiſſe made in the ſayde ſupplication, that is, to repeale al lawes and Statutes, made contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry to the ſayde ſupre macye, and Sea Apoſtolyke, durynge the ſayde ſciſme, the whiche is to be vnderſtand, ſynce the .xx. yeare of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reigne of the ſayde late kyng Henry theyght, and ſo the ſayde lorde Legate doth accepte and recogniſe the ſame.</p>
            <p>Wherein the pacliament begonne and holden at Weſtminſter, in the .xxi. yeare of the raygne of the late Kyng of mooſt famous memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye, kynge Henry theight one acte was then and there made agaynſt pluralities of benefices, for takynge of farmes by ſpirituall men and for none reſidence, in the which acte amongeſt other thinges it was ordeyned and enacted, that yf any perſon or perſones, at any tyme af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter the fyrſt day of Apryll, in the yeare of our Lord God a thouſand fyue hundred and thyrtie contrary to the ſame acte, ſhould procure and obtayne at the court of Rome, or elles where any licence, or ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cences, vnion, tolleration, or diſpenſation, to receaue and take anye more benefices, with cure, then was limitted and appoynted by the ſame acte, or elles at any tyme after the ſayde daye ſhoulde put in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution any ſuch licence, tolleration, or diſpenſation, before that tyme obteyned, contrary to the ſayde Acte, that then euery ſuche perſon or perſones, ſo after the ſayd daye, ſuinge for hym ſelfe, or receauyng, &amp; takyng ſuch benefice by force of ſuch licence or lycences, vnione, tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration, or diſpenſation, that is to ſay: the ſame prrſon or perſonnes onely, and no nother, ſhoulde for euery ſuch default, incurre the dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger payne, and penaltite of .xx. li. ſterl. and ſhoulde alſo looſe the hole profytes of euery ſuche benefice, or benefices, as he receaueth, or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="xii" facs="tcp:150877:15"/>by force of any ſuch licence, or licences, vnion, tolleration or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation. And where alſo in the ſayde Acte it was ordeyned and en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>acted, that yf any perſon or perſones dyd procure, or obtayne at the Courte of Rome, or ells where any maner of lycence, or diſpenſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be none reſidence at their dignities, prebende, or benefices, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trari to the ſayde Acte, that then euery ſuch perſon or perſons, puttynge in execution any ſuch diſpenſation, or licence for hym ſelfe from the ſayd firſt day of Apryll, in the ſayde yeare of our Lorde God, a M. fiue hundred, and thyrtie ſhould runne and encurre, in the penaltye, damage, and payne of .xx. li. ſter. for euery tyme ſo doyng, to the for fayted and recouered, as by the ſayde Acte is declared. And yet ſuch licence, or diſpenſation ſo procured, or to be put in execution, to bee voyde, and of none effect, as by the ſame acte more playnely it doth, and may appeare.</p>
            <p>Be it enacted by thaucthoritie of this preſent parliament, that as muche onely of the ſayd Acte as concerneth the articles, and clauſes aforeſayd, and al and euery the wordes and ſentences, contayned in the ſayd Acte, concernyng the ſayd articles, and clauſes, and euerye of them, ſhall from henceforth be repealed, adnulled, reuoked, adnichi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lated, and vtterly made voyde for euer. Any thyng in the ſayde acte to the contrary in any wiſe, notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>And where alſo at the ſeſſion of the ſame parliament, holden vpon prorogation, in the .xxiii. yeare of the reigne of the ſayde late kynge Henry theyght, one act, entituled: the acte that no perſon ſhalbe cited out of the dioceſſe, where he or ſhe dwelleth, except in certayne caces, And where alſo at the ſayd parliament, in the ſeſſion holden at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter vpon prorogation, in the .xxiiii. yeare of the raigne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd late kyng Henry theyght, one act was made, that appeales in ſuche caſes as hath bene vſed to be purſued to the ſea of Rome, ſhoulde not from henceforth be had nor vſed, but within this realme. And where alſo at the ſayd parliament holden at Weſtminſter, in the .xxi. year of the raygne of the ſayde late kynge Henry the eyght, and there conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued by diuers prorogations, vntyll the .xiiii. daye of Aprill, in the xxvii. yeare of his reygne, one acte was made concerning reſtraintes of paymentes of annaties, and fyrſte fruites, of Archebyſhopryckes and Byſhoprickes of the Sea of Rome. And where at a Seſſion of the ſayde parliament, holden in the .xxv. yeare of the reygne of the ſayde late kyng, there was alſo made one acte, entituled: the ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the clergye to the kynges maieſties, and one other acte entitu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led, one Acte reſtraynyng the ſayde paymentes of annates, or fyrſte fruites to the byſhop of Rome, and of the electing and conſecratinge of the Archbyſhoppes and Byſhopes within this realme. And one other act was then and there made, entituled: an act concerninge the exoneration of the kinges ſubiectes, from exactions, and impoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
<pb facs="tcp:150877:16"/>before that tyme payde to the Sea of Rome, and for hauing licences and diſpenſacions within this realme, without ſuyng further for the ſame.</p>
            <p>Be it enacted by thauctoritie of this preſent perliament, that the ſayde ſeueral actes made for the reſtraynt of the payment of the ſayd annates, and fyrſte fruytes, and all other the ſayd Actes, made in the ſayde .xxiiii. and .xxv. yeares of the raygne of the ſayd late kyng, and euery of them, and al, and euery braunch, article, matter, and ſentence in them, and euery of them conteyned, ſhalbe by thaucthoritie of this preſente parlament from henceforth vtterlye voyde, made fruſtrate and repelled, to all intentes, conſtructions, and purpoſes.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthoritie of this preſent parlia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment. that all and euery theſe actes folowinge. That is to ſaye: one acte made at the ſeſſion of the ſayde parliament holden vpon proroga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion at Weſtin. in the .xxvi. yeare of the raigne of the ſayde late kyng Henry theyght, entituled: an acte concerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kynges hyghnes to be ſupreame heade of the church of Englande, and to haue aucthoritie to reforme and redreſſe all errours, hereſies, and abuſes, in the ſame. And one other acte made in the ſame ſeſſion of the ſame parliamente entituled: an acte for nomination, and conſecration of Suffragans within this realme. And one other acte made in the .xxvii. yeare of the reygne of theſayde late kynge Henry the eyght, intituled: an acte wherby the kynge ſhoulde haue power to nominate .xxxii. perſons of his Clergye and Laye fee, for makynge of Eccleſiaſticall lawes. And alſo one other acte, made at the parliamente holden at Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter in the .xxviii. yeare of the reygne of the ſayd late kyng Henry the eyght entituled: an acte extinquyſſhynge thaucthoritie of the Byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome And one other acte made in the ſame parliamente, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tytuled: an acte for the releaſe of ſuch, as then had, obteyned, preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded lycences, and dyſpenſations from the Sea of Rome. And alſo all that parte of theacte, made in the ſayde .xxviii. yeare of the ſayde kynge, entituled: an acte for the eſtablyſhemente of the Succeſſion of the imperiall crowne of the realme, that concerneth a prohibition to marrye within the degrees expreſſed in the ſayde Acte. And alſo one other Acte, made at the parliamente holden at Weſtminſter, in the .xxxi. yeare of the reygne of the ſayde late kynge Henrye the eyghte, eutituled: an acte aucthoriſynge the kynges highnes to make Byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes by his letters patentes. And one other acte made in the ſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of the ſame parliament, begon in the ſayd .xxx. yeare, holden vpon prorogation. the .xxxii. yeare of the reygne of the ſayde Kynge Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the eyghte, entituled: an acte concernynge precontractes of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryages, and touchinge degrees of conſanguinitie. And one other acte made in the parliament holden at Weſtminſter, in the .xxxv. yeare of the reygne of the ſayd late kynge Henry theyght, entituled: an act for
<pb n="xvi" facs="tcp:150877:16"/>the ratification of the kinges maieſties ſtile, ſhall henceforth be repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, made fruſtrate, voyde, and of none effect. And where alſo at the ſaid parliament holden at Weſtminſter, in the .xxxv. yeare of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> raign of the ſayd late kyng Henry theyght, one other acte was made, entite led: an Acte concerning the eſtablyſhment of the ſucceſſion of the ſayd king in the Imperial Crowne of this realme: In the which act there is a forme of a corporall othe deuiſed and ſet forth, that euerye ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte of this realme, ſhould be bound to take agaynſt the power, auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and iuriſdiction of the Sea of Rome. Be it enacted bi y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> auc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thoritie of this preſent Parliament, that ſo muche of the ſayd Acte, as toucheth the ſayde othe agaynſt the ſupremacy, and all othes ther vp on had, made, and gyuen, ſhalbe from henceforth vtterly voide, repea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led and of none effect. And where alſo one other act was made in the xxxvii. yeare of the raygne of the ſayd late kyng Henry theight enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, an acte that doctours of ciuill law, beyng married, myghte ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercyſe eccleſiaſtical iuriſdiction. Be it enacted bi thaucthoritie of this preſent Parliament, that the ſayd acte laſt before mentioned, and all, and euery braunche, article, ſentence, and matter, conteyned in the ſame, ſhall from henceforth be repealed, and vtterly made voyde, and of none effect.</p>
            <p>And where one other acte was made at the firſt ſeſſion of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, holden at Weſtminſter, in the firſt yeare of the raigne of king Edwarde the ſix te, entituled: an acte for the repeale of certayne Sta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures, concerning treaſons, felonies, &amp;c. In the which acte amongeſt other thinges, there is contayned certeyne prouiſions, paynes, penal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties, and forfaytures for and agaynſt ſuche, as ſhoulde by open prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chinges, expreſſe wordes, ſayinges, writinge, printing ouert dede, or acte affirme, or ſet forth, that the kyng of this realme for the tyme be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing, is not or ought not to be ſupreame heade in earth, of the churches of England and Irelande, ne of any of them, or that the Byſhoppe of Rome, or any other perſon, or perſons, other then the kynge of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande for the tyme being, is or ought to be ſupreame heade of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame churches, or any of them, as in the ſame acte laſt before reherſed, more at large is contained, and may appeare. Be it enacted by thauctoritie of this preſent Parliament, that theſe clauſes before reherſed, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the ſayd acte, concerning the ſupremacye, and all, and euerye braunche, article, wordes, and ſentence, in the ſame ſounding, or ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng to the derogation of the ſupremacie, of the popes holines, or the Sea of Rome, and al paynes, penalties, &amp; forfaytures. made againſt them, that ſhould by any meanes ſet forth, or extole the ſayd ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cie, ſhalbe from henceforth vtterly voyde and of none effecte.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayd, that al clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſentences, and articles of euery other Statute, or act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, made ſithenes the ſayd .xx. yeare of the raygne of kyng Henry
<pb facs="tcp:150877:17"/>theyght, againſt the ſupreame aucthoritie of the Popes holynes, or Sea Apoſtolike of Rome, or conteining ani other matter of the ſame effecte onely, that is repealed in any of the Statutes aforeſayd, ſhall be alſo by aucthoritie hereof from henceforth vtterly voide, fruſtrate and of none effect.</p>
            <p>And where we your moſt humble ſubiectes, the Lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and commons in this preſent Parliament aſſembled, haue exhibited to your Maieſties one other ſupplication in forme fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowinge.</p>
            <p>We the lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and the commons in thys preſent Parliament aſſembled repreſenting the whole body of thys realme, reduced and receaued by your maieſties interceſſion to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie of Chriſtes Churche, and the obedience of the Sea Apoſtolike of Rome, and the Popes holines gouerning the ſame, make moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſuite vnto your maieſties, to be likewiſe meanes &amp; interceſſours, that al occaſions of contention, hatred, grudge, ſuſpition, and trouble both outwardly and inwardly in mens conſciences, whyche myghte aryſe amongeſt vs, by reaſon of diſobedience, may bi auctoritie of the Popes holynes, and by miniſtration of the ſame vnto vs, by the moſt reuerend father in God, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord Cardinal Poole, by diſpenſation to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration, or permiſſion reſpectiuely, as the cace ſhall require, be aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and taken awaye, and by aucthoritie ſufficient theſe articles fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, and generally all others, when any occaſion ſhall ſo require, may be prouided for, and confyrmed.</p>
            <p>Fyrſt that all Byſſhopryckes, cathedrall churches, hoſpitales, colle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, lcholes, and other ſuch foundations nowe continuing, made by aucthoritie of Parlyament, or otherwyſe eſtablyſhed, accordyng to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ordre of the lawes of thys realme, ſythens this ſcyſme, may be confyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med and contynued for euer.</p>
            <p>Item that marriages made <hi>infragradus prohibitos conſanguinitatis, affinitatis, cog<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nationis ſpiritualis,</hi> or which myght be made voyde <hi>propter impedimentum publicae honeſtatis, iuſtitiae,</hi> or for any other cauſe, prohibited by the canons onelye maye be confirmed, and chyldren borne of thoſe marriages declared legittimate, ſo as thoſe marriages were made, according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawes of the realme for the time being, and be not directly againſt the lawes of God, nor in ſuch caſe, as the Sea Apoſtolike hath not vſed to dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence wythall.</p>
            <p>That inſtitutions of benefices, and other promotions eccleſiaſtical and diſpenſations, made according to the forme of the acte of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, may be likewiſe confirmed.</p>
            <p>That all iudiciall proceſſes, made before anye ordinaries of thys realme, or before any delegates vpon any appeales, according to thor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre. of the lawes of the realine, may be likewiſe ratified &amp; confirmed.</p>
            <p>And finally where certayne actes and ſtatutes haue bene made in
<pb n="xvii" facs="tcp:150877:17"/>the tyme of the late ſciſm, concerning the landes, and hereditamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of Archebiſſhoprykes and Biſhoprickes, the ſuppreſſion, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolution of monaſteries. Abbayes, prioryes, chauntries, colleges, and al other the goodes and cartels of religious houſes. Synce the why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che tyme, the ryght, and dominion of certayne landes, and heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, goodes and cattels, belongynge to the ſame, be diſperſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade, and come to the handes, and poſſeſſions of diuerſe and ſondri perſons, wholby gyfte, purchaſe, exchaunge, and other meanes, accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge to the order of the lawes and ſtatutes of this realme, for the tyme veynge, haue the ſame. For the auoydinge of all ſcruples that might growe by any thoccaſions aforeſayd, or by any other waies, or meanes, whatſoeuer: It may pleaſe youre maieſties, to be interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, and medtatours, to the ſayde mooſte reuerende father, Cardi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nall Pole, that all ſuch cauſes, and quarels as by pretence of the ſaid ſciſme, or by any other occaſion, or meane whatſoeuer, myght be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the Popes holynes, or Sea Apoſtolike, or by any other iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction Eccleſiaſticall, may be vtterly remoued, and taken awaye, ſo as al perſones hauing ſufficient conueyaunce of the ſayd landes and hereditamentes, goodes and cattels, as is aforeſayd, by the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lawes, actes or Statutes of this realme, maye withoute ſcruple of conſcience, enioye them wythout impechement or trouble by prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of any generall counſayle, Cannons, or Eccleſiaſtical lawes, &amp; cleare from all daungers of the cenſures of the churche.</p>
            <p>And conformablie herevnto, the Byſſhoppes and Cleagry of the prouynce of Cantorburie haue preſented to your maieſties a ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, in this tenour that foloweth.</p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="lat">
                  <body>
                     <div type="supplication">
                        <p>
                           <hi>Nos Epiſcopi &amp; Clerus Cantuarienſis prouinciae in hoc Synodo more noſtro ſolito, dum Regni parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celebratur, congregati, cum omni debi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ta humilitate &amp; reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia ex ponimus Maieſtatibus uestris, quod lic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>t Ec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cleſiarum, quibus in Epiſcopos Decanos, Archidiaconos, rectores, &amp; uica<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rios praefecti ſumus, &amp; animaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, quae nobis &amp; curae nostrae ſubiectae ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; earundem bonorum iuriſdictionum, &amp; iurium, ex ſacrorum Canonum diſpoſitione, defenſores &amp; curatores constituti ſumus, &amp; proptereaipſa rum bona, iuriſdictiones, &amp; iura in pernicioſo huius Regni praeterito ſciſ mate de perdita &amp; amiſſa, omniſtudio, &amp; totis noſtris uiribus, recuperare &amp; ad pristinum Eccleſiarum ius reuocare, iuris remedijs niti deberemus: Nichilominus camen habito prius per nos ſuper hac re maturo Conſilio, et deliberatione ingenuè fatemur, nos optimè cognoſcere, quàm haec bonoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Eccleſiasticoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> difficilis, &amp; quaſi impnſsibilis eſſet recuperatio propter multiplices, ac pene inextricabiles ſuper hiis habitos contractus, &amp; diſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitiones,
<pb facs="tcp:150877:18"/>&amp; quod ſi ea tentaretur, quies &amp; tranquilitas Regni facilè per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbaretur, &amp; unitas Eccleſiae Catholicae, quae iam pietatis, &amp; aucthorita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te Maieſtatum ueſtrarum hoc in Regno introducta eſt, cum maxima dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultate ſuum debitum progreſſum, &amp; finem ſortirl poſſet. Ideo nos bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; quietem publicam priuatis commoditatibus, &amp; ſalutem tot animarum praetioſo Chriſti ſanguine et redemptarum terrenis bonis antepone<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, &amp; non quae noctra, ſed quae leſu Christiſunt quaerentes, Maiectatis uestras enixè rogamus, eiſ<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> humiliter ſupplicamus, ut reueren diſsimo in Chricto patri, domino Reginaldo Cardinali Polo, ad ipſas, &amp; uniuerſum hoc An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gliae regnum ſanctiſsimi domini nostri, Domini Iulij, Papae tertij, &amp; Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicae ſedes de latere legato, haec nomine nostro in ſinuare, &amp; apud eu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tercedere digne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur, ut in hiis bonis Eccleſiastices in parte, uel in toto arbi trio ſuo iuxta facultates ſibi ab eodem ſanctiſsimo domino nostro Papa conceſſas, eorundem bonorum detentoribus elargiendis et relaxandis pub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>licum bonum priuato pacem &amp; tranquillitatem diſsidijs, &amp; perturbatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus, at<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> animarum falutem bono terrenis praeferre, &amp; anteponere uelit Nos enim in omnibus quae ab ipſo legato ſtatuta, &amp; ordinata circa haec bona fuerint, ex nunc, prout ex tunc, &amp; econtra co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſenſum nostru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> praecta mus, imo etiam ut in praemiſsis ſe difficilem aut restrictum reddere non uelit, malestatis uestrae nostro nomine eum hortari, &amp; rogare dignabun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. In ſuper maiestatibus uestris ſupplicamus, ut pro ſua pietate effice re dignentur, ut ea quae ad iuriſdistionem noctra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; libertate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Eccleſiasti cam pertinent, ſine quibus debitum nostri pastorales officij et curae anima rum nobis commiſſae exercere non poſſumus, nobis ſuperiorum temporu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in iuria ablata restituantur, &amp; ea nobis, &amp; Eccleſijs perpetuo illeſa &amp; ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua permaneant, &amp; ut omnes leges, quae hanc noſtram, iuriſdictionem, &amp; libertatem Eccleſiaſticam tollunt, ſeu quouis modo impediunt, abrogen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ad honorem dei, &amp; maieſtatum ueſtrarum, &amp; uniuerſihuius Regni Spirituale, et temporale commodum, et ſalutem, certam, ſpem etiam habe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                              <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, Maieſtates ueſtras, pro ſua ſingulari in ipſum deum pietate, pro<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> mul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tis et inſignibus ab ipſius dei bonitate acceptis beneficijs neceſsitatibus, et incommodis huius ſui Regni Eccleſiarum maximê curam animarum habentium nun<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> defuturas eſſe, ſedprout opus fuerit, conſulturas at<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiſuras.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Foraſmuch as the ſayde mooſt reuerend father, the Lorde Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate, at the interceſſion of your maieſties, hath by thauctoritie of the Sea Apoſtolyke, ſufficiently diſpenſed in the matters ſpecified in the ſayd ſeuerall ſupplications, as in his ſayd letters of diſpenſation is conteyned more at large. The tenor wherof enſueth.</p>
            <pb n="xviii" facs="tcp:150877:18"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="lat">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Reginaldus miſeratione diuina Sanstae Mariae in Coſmedin Sanctae Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>manae Eccleſiae, Diaconus, Cardinalis Polus nuncupatus, ad Sereniſsimos Philippum &amp; Mariam, Angliae Reges, fidei defenſores: et uniuerſum An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gliae regnum, Sanctiſsimi Domini nostri Papae, et ſedis Apostolicae de la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tere legatus eiſ dem Sereniſsimis Philippo et Mariae Regibus ſalutem in Domino ſempiternam. Cùm ſupremum conſilium istius regni parlamentu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nuncupatum Maiestatibus uestris, per ſuos ſupplices libellos expoſuiſſet, quòd perniciociſsimo ſciſmate, in hoc regno aliâs uigente, quod nunc deï miſericordia, &amp; maiestatum ueſtrarum pietate extinctum est, authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ipſius parlamenti, nonnulli Epiſcopatus diuiſi, &amp; ex his aliquae infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riores Eccleſiae, in cathedrales erestae, et ſcholae, at que hoſpitalia fundata, necnon plurimae dispenſationes et beneficiorum prouiſiones factae fueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ac multae perſonae quibus perſuaſum fuerat: Iuris Canonici dispoſitiones, hoc in Regno amplius locum non habere: inter ſe in gradibus conſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatis uel affinitatis de iure prohibitis, &amp; alijs impedimentis Canonicis ſibi obſtantibus matrimonia, per uerba de praeſenti co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>traxerunt, et multis actus iudiciarij, &amp; proceſſus, tam in primis, quàm ulterioribus inſtantiis ſuper rebus ſpiritualibus, &amp; Eccleſiaſticis coram iudicibus tam Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rijs quàm delegatis, qui authoritate laicali procedebant, habiti &amp; ſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, adſuper eis etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiae latae, et promulgatae fueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, et bona eccleſiaſtica per diuerſas eiuſdem regni perſonas occupata, et apprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſa fuerunt: Quae quidem licet ex ſacrorum Canonum institutis irrita declarari poſſent, ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>menſi ad alium ſtatum, quàm in quo nuncſunt, reuocarentur, publica pax &amp; quies uniuerſi regni turbaretur, et maxima confuſio oriretur, preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim ſi dictorum bonorum poſſeſſores moleſtarentur, et propterea maiestati bus ueſtris humiliter ſupplicauerint, ut apud nos intercedere dignentur, ut premiſſarum rerum firmitari, et ſtabilitati, et ſimul huius Regni quieti, et tranquillitati de benignitate Apoſtolica prouidere uelimus. Cumque Epiſcopi quoque deindè, ac reliquus prouinciae Cantuarienſis Clerus totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fere corpus Eccleſiasticum regni repreſentans, ad quos haec bonorum Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticorum cauſa maximè pertinet, expoſuerint, quòd haec bona ad ius eccleſiarum reuocare non poſſunt, quin pax uniuerſalis, &amp; quies huius reg<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ni turbetur, et cauſa fidei at<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> unitatis Eccleſiae, iam toto omnium conſen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſu hoc in regno introducta, in maximum periculum adducatur, et propte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea ipſi quoque ſupplicauerint, ut apud nos intercedere uelint, ut in his bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nis Eccleſiasticis poſſeſſoribus relaxandus reſtricti et difficiles eſſe nolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, maieſtates autem ueſtrae, ad quas maxime ſpectat prouldere, ut regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ipſaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poteſtari, regimini et curae commiſſum in pace et tranquillitatecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruetur.
<pb facs="tcp:150877:19"/>His ſupplicationibus et postulatis cognitis et mature co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideratis iudicauerint ea omnia, et maxime illa, quae in bonoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eccleſiasticoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cauſa petuntur, pro cauſa fidei et pro pace publica, per nos debere ſine ulla dilatio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cedi, et que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>admodu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rogatae fueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, apud nos intercedere dignatae fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint, prout in ſupplicationibus per idem ſupremum conſilium, et epiſcopos ac clerum praefatum maiestatibus ueſtris porrectis, atque in libello inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsionis per eaſdem maiestates uestras nobis ſimul cum alijs ſupplicatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus exhibito, latius apparet. Idcirco nos qui ad maiestates uestras, et hoc nobiliſsimum uestrum regnum à Sanctiſsimo Domino noſtro Iulio Papa tertio ipſius et ſedis Apoſtolicae de latere legati miſsi ſumus, ut regnum iſtud, quod iamdiu ab Eccleſiae Catholicae unitate ſeparatum fuerat, Deo et Eccleſiae Christi, eiuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> in terris uicario reconciliaremus: et ut ea omnia quae ad pace<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> et tranquillitatem huius regni pertinerent, omni ſtudio pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curaremus, poſtqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dei benignitate, et maiestatem ueſtrarum pietate, per authoritatem eiuſdem Sanctiſsimi Domini noſtri Papae, cuius uices hic ſustinemus, reconciliatio iam facta est, ut paci et tranquillitati regni prae fati conſulamus, atque ut unitas eccleſiae, ex qua ſalus tot animarum prae cioſo Chriſti ſanguine redemptarum dependet, hoc in regno iam introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta corrobaretur, &amp; ſalua permaneat, cùm utriuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> rei ſtabilitatem in eo maxime conſiſtere, ſi horum Eccleſiaſticorum bonorum poſſeſſoribus mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lestia nulla inferatur quo nimus ea teneant, tot et tam grauia teſtimonia nobis fidem faciant, et maieſtatum ueſtrarum interceſsio, quae pro unitate Eccleſiae, et ſedis Apostolicae auctoritate hoc in regno inſtauranda tam ſtudioſè, et tam piè elaborarunt, eam quam par eſt auctoritatem apud nos habeat, et ut uniuerſum hoc regnum ſedis Apoſtolicae maternam uerè in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, et charitatem erga ſe agnoſcat, et re ipſa experiatur: quoſcun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ad quos infra ſcripta pertine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, à quibuſuis excommunicationis, ſuſpenſio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nis, et interdicti, alijs<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> eccleſiaſticis ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tijs, ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuris, et poenis à iure, uel ab homine quauis occaſione uel cauſa latis, ſi quibus quomodolibet innodati existunt, ad effectum praeſentium dumtaxat conſequendum harum ſerie abſoluentes, et abſolutos fore cenſentes, aucthoritate Apoſtolica, per litte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ras Sanctiſsimi domini noſtri, domini Iulij Papae tertij nobis conceſſa, &amp; qua fungimur in hac parte, tenore praeſentium diſpenſamus: quòd omnes et ſingulae Cathedralium Eccleſiarum erectiones, hoſpitalium, et ſcholaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fundationes tempore praeteriti ſciſmatis, licet de facto et nulliter atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tatae in eo ſtatu, in quo nunc ſunt, perpetuo firmae et ſtabiles parmaneant, illiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que Apoſtolicae firmitatis robur adijcimus, ita ut non ea aucthoritate, qua prius, ſed ea, quam nunc eis tribuimus, factae ab omnibus cenſeantur, &amp; cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <pb n="xix" facs="tcp:150877:19"/>omnibus et ſingulis perſonis regni praedicti, quae in aliquo conſanguinita tis uel affinitatis gradu etiam multiplici, uel cognationis ſpiritualie, ſeu publicae honestatis iusticiae impedimento de iure poſitiuo introductis, &amp; in quibus ſanstiſsimus dominus noſter Papa dispenſare cönſueuit, matri monia ſcienter uelignorantur de facto contraxerint, ut alique impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> torum premiſſorum, non obstante in eorum matrimonijs, ſic contractis li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere, &amp; licite remanere, ſeu illa de nouo contrahere poſsint, miſericorditer in domino dispenſamus, prolem ſuſceptam, ſuſcipiendam legitimam, de cernentes, ita tamen ùt qui ſcienter et malitioſè contraxerint, à ſententia exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municationis, et ab inceſtus ſeu ſacrilegij reatu, abſolutione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>â ſuo ordi nario, uel curato, quibus id faciendi facultatem concedimus, obtineant, ac omnes Eccleſiaſticas ſeculares, ſeu quorumuis ordinum regulares perſonas quae aliquas impetrationes, dispenſationes, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceſsiones, gratias, et indulta tam Ordines quàm beneficia Eccleſiastica, ſeu alias ſpirituales materias praetenſa aucthoritate ſupremitatis Eccleſiae Anglicanae licet nulliter, et de facto obtinuerint, et ad correuerſae Eccleſiae unitati restitutae fuerint, in ſuis Ordinibus, &amp; beneficijs per nos ipſos, ſeu â nobis ad id deputatos, miſericorditer recipiemus, prout iam multae receptae fueru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſecum<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſuper his opportunè in Domino diſpenſauimus: Ac omnes proceſſus in quibuſuis instantijs coram quibuſuis iudicibus, tam ordinariis quâm delegatis, etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> laicis ſuper materijs ſpiritualibus habitos &amp; formatos, &amp; ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tias ſuper eis latas, licet nulliter et de facto, quoad nullitatem ex defectu iuriſdictio nis praefato tantum inſurgentem ſanamus, illoſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>, et illas aucthoritate A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postolica confirmamus: Ac quibuſuis huius regni perſonis, ad quarum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus bona Eccleſiastica ex quocun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> contractu ſeu titulo oneroſo uel lucra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuo iam deuenerint, illaque tenuerint, ſeu etiam teneant, omnes &amp; quoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> fructus ex eiſde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bonis, licet indebitê perceptos, in totum remitt imus &amp; relaxamus. Volentes ac decernentes, quòd dictorum bonorum Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>asticorum tam mobilium quàm immobilium poſſeſſores praefati non poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſintin praeſenti, nec in posterum, ſeu per conſiliorum generalium, uel pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincialium dispoſitiones, ſeu decretales Romanoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pontificum Epiſtolas, ſeu aliam quamcun<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> cenſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eccleſiaſtica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in dictis bonis, ſeu eorunde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeſsione molestari, inquietari, uel perturbari, nec eis aliquae ce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſurae uel poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae eccleſiasticae propter huiuſmodi detentionem, ſeu non reſtitutione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> irro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gari uel infligi, et ſic per quoſcunque iudices, &amp; auditores ſublata eis, qua ſuis aliter iudicandi et interpretandi facultate, et aucthoritate iudicari et diffiniri debere, &amp; quicquid ſecus attemptari contigerit, irritum et inane fore decernimus, non obſtantibus praemiſsis defectibus, &amp; quibuſuis
<pb facs="tcp:150877:20"/>Apostolicis, ac in prouincialibus, et ſinodalibus concilijs editis, ſpecialibus uel generalibus conſtitutionibus, &amp; ordinationibus, caeteriſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan>ue contrarijs quibuſcunque. Admonemus tamen cùm diuiſio Epiſcopatuum, &amp; erectio Cathedralium Eccleſiarum ſint de maioribus cauſis, quae ſummo pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci ſunt reſeruatae, recurrendum eſſe ad ſuam Sanctitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ab ea ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citer postulandum, ut haec confirmare, ſeu de nouo facere dignetur. Et licet omnes res mobiles Eccleſiarum indistinctêijs, qui eos tenent relaxaueri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, eos tamen admonitos eſſe uolumus, ut ante oculos habentes diuini iudicij ſeueritatem contra Balthaſarem Regem Babilonis, qui uaſa ſacra non à ſe, ſed à patre ê templo ablata in prophanos uſus conuertit ea proprijs Eccleſijs ſi extant, uel alijs reſtituant. Hortantes etiam, &amp; per uiſcera mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſericordiae leſu Christi obtestantes eos omnes, quos haec res tangit, ut ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ſuae non omnino immemores, hoc ſaltem efficiant, ut ex bonis Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticis, maxime ijs, quae ratione perſonatuum &amp; uicariatuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> populi ministro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſuſtentationi fuerint ſpecialiter deſtinata, ſeu alijs Cathedralibus, &amp; alijs quae nunc extant, inferioribus Eccleſijs curam animarum exercenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ita prouideatur, ut earum paſtores, perſonae &amp; uicarij commodè, &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e iuxta eorum qualitatem, &amp; ſtatum ſuſtentari poſſint, &amp; curam a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimarum laudabiliter exercere, &amp; onera incumbentia congruè ſupporta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. </hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Datum Lambeth prope Londinum VVintonien<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Dioceſſ.</hi>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Anno Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitatis domini Milleſimo, quingenteſimo, quinquageſimo quarto. Nono Cal. Ianuarij Pontif. Sanctiſsimi in Christo patris, &amp; Domini nostri, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini Iulij, diuina prouidentia Papae tertij. Anno quinto.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Reginaldus Cardinalis Polus Legatus.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>We the ſayd lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and commons in thys preſent parliament aſſembled, rendryng moſt humble thankes to your maieſties, by whoſe interceſſion and meanes we haue obteyned the ſayd diſpenſations of the popes holynes by the ſayd moſte reuerende father in God, hyslegate, moſt humbly beſecheth the ſame, that it may be ordeined as foloweth.</p>
            <p>And therfore be it enacted by thaucthoritie of this preſent parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that al, &amp; ſinguler articles &amp; clauſes. conteined in the ſaid diſpenſation, as well touchyng the eſtablyſhment of Byſſhoprykes, and cathedrall churches, as alſo the confirmation of marriages in degrees prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the canons of the churche, the legittimation of chyldren, and the ratification of proceſſe, and of ſentences in matters eccleſiaſticall, touchyng the inualiditie of them for wante of iuridiction, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſititutions and deſtitutions, of, and in benefices and promotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall, diſpenſations, and graces, gyuen by ſuche order, as the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke lawes of the realme then approued, and all other thynges before
<pb n="xx" facs="tcp:150877:20"/>conteyned in the ſayd letters of diſpenſation, ſhall remayne and be re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>puted and taken, to al intentes and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtructions in the lawes of this realme, lawful, good, and effectuall to be alleaged and pleaded in all courtes eccleſiaſticall and temporall, for good and ſufficiente matter, eyther for the playntyfe or defendaunt, without any alle gation, or ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iection, to be made againſt the validitie of them, by pretence of any ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nerall counſayle, canon, or decree, to the contrary made, or to be made in that behalfe.</p>
            <p>And where as diuerſe and ſondrye late Monaſteries, Priories, Commaundries, Nonneries, Deaneries, Prebendes, Colleges, Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pitalles, Howſes of friars, Chauntries, and other religious and eccle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiaſtical houſes and places, and the mannours, graunges, meſuages, landes, tenementes, rectories, tithes, pentions, portions, vicareges, churches, chappels, aduouſons, nominations, patronages, annuities rentes, reuertions, ſeruices, and other poſſeſſions, and hereditamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes to the ſayd late monaſteries. priories, nonneries, commaundries, deanryes, chauntries, prebendes, houſes of Fryars, colleges, hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talles, and other religious and eccleſiaſtical houſes and places and to ſondrye Archebyſſhoprykes, and Byſſhoprykes within this realme, late appartaynyng and belongyng, came aſwell to the handes &amp; poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the ſayd kyng of famous memory Henrye theyghte, father vnto your maieſtie, our ſayd ſoueraygne Lady by diſſolution, gyfte, graunt, ſurrendre, attayndre, or otherwyſe, as alſo to the handes and poſſeſſion of diuers and ſondry other perſons, and bodyes polytyke and corporate, by ſondry meanes, conueyaunces, and aſſuraunces, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to the ordre of the lawes and ſtatutes of this realme.</p>
            <p>And where alſo diuerſe manours, landes, tenementes, and heredi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tamentes percell of the poſſeſſions of Archebyſſhoprykes and Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rykes, and many and ſondrye late deaneryes, colleges, chauntryes, rectories, Prebendes, Free chappels, Guyldes, and Fraternities, manours, houſes, Graunges, landes, tenementes, rentes, ſeruyces, and other Eccleſiaſticall poſſeſſions, and hereditamentes, goodes, and cattels to the ſayd Archebyſſhoprykes, Byſſhoprykes, deanries, colleges, chauntries, free chappels, rectories, guyldes, and fraterm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, late appertayning, and belongyng, or appoynting, to and for the fynding of prieſtes obyttes, lyghtes, or other lyke purpoſe, came as wel to the handes &amp; poſſeſſion of the lare noble kyng Edward the ſixt brother vnto your maieſtie ſoueraygne Lady, by vertue of an acte of parliament thereof made, or otherwiſe, as alſo to the handes and poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeſſion of diuerſe and ſondry other perſons, and bodies polytyke and corporate by ſondry meanes, conueyaunces, and aſſuraunces, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ordre of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawes of this realme: a great nombre, of which ſayd late monaſteries, priories, nonneries, commaundries, deaneries colleges, hoſpitalles, prebendes, chauntries, free chappelles, guildes,
<pb facs="tcp:150877:21"/>and, fraternities, and the mannours, granges, meſuages, landes, tene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes, rentes, reuercions, ſeruyces, tythes, pentions, portions vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reges, churches, chappeles, aduouſons, nominations, patronages, an nuities, and hereditamentes, goodes, and cattels, to the ſayd monaſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ries, pryoryes, nonneryes, commaundries, deaneries, colleges, hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talles, chauntries, free chappelles, guyldes fraternities, and other ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſtaſticall houſes, Archebyſſhoprykes, and Byſſhoprykes, belonging as well for great ſommes of moneye, as for other good, and reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble cauſes and conſiderations, haue bene conueyed and aſſured to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe the ſubiectes, and bodyes polytyke of this realme, aſwel by the ſayd kyng Henrye theyght, the ſayd kyng Edward the ſyxte, and by your hyghnes our ſoueraygne Ladye, and ioyntely by both your ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ieſties, as alſo by diuerſe the owners of the ſayd eccleſiaſticall poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whych ſayd conueyaunces and aſſuraunces by their ſondrye let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters patentes, and other wrytynges more playnelye do and mayap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. Foraſmuche as the ſayd moſt reuerende father hath alſo bythe ſayd diſpenſations, remoued and taken away al matter of empeache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, trouble, and daunger, whyche by occaſion of any generall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayle, canon, or decree eccleſiaſticall myghte touche and diſquiete the poſſeſſions of ſuch goodes moueable, landes, tenementes, poſſeſſions and hereditamentes, as were of late belongyng to anye of the ſayd Archebyſſhoprykes, Byſſhoprykes, monaſteries, prioryes, nonneries commaundries, deaneryes, colleges, chauntries, prebendes, rectori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, hoſpitalles, houſes of fryars, or other religious and eccleſiaſticall houſes, and places, of what nature, name, kind, or qualitie ſoeuer they be of. Yet for that the title of allandes, poſſeſſions, and hereditamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in thys your maieſties realme and dominions is grounded in the lawes, ſtatutes, and cuſtomes of the ſame, and by your highe iuriſdic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, aucthoritie royall, and crowne imperiall, and in your courtes on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye to be impleaded, ordered, tryed, and iudged, and none otherwyſe, and vnderſtandyng, that the whole, full, and moſte gratious intentes mynd and determination of your moſt excellent maieſties be, that all, and euery perſon and perſons, bodyes polytyke and corporate, theyr heyres, ſucceſſours, and aſſignes, and euery of them, ſhal haue, kepe, retayne, and enioye all, and euery their eſtates, ryghtes, poſſeſſions, and intereſtes, that they and euery of them nowe hathe, or hereafter ſhall haue, of, and in al and euery the mannours, graunges, meſuages landes, tenementes, tithes, pentions, portions, aduouſons, nominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, patronages, anuities, rentes, reuercions, ſeruices, hundredes, wapentakes, liberties, frauncheſis, and other the poſſeſſions and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditamentes of the ſayd moneſteries, abbeyes, pryoryes, nonneryes commaundries, deaneries colleges, prebendes, hoſpitales, houſes of fryars, chauntries, rectories, vicareges, churches, chappelles, Arche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſſhoprykes, and Byſſhoprykes, and other religious or eccleſiaſtical
<pb n="xxiii" facs="tcp:150877:21"/>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="4 pages">
                  <desc>〈4 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtanding.</p>
            <p>And where as by diſſolution of monaſteries, and other religious houſes, certayne paryſhe churches and chappels which were before exempte, from the iuriſdiction of the Archbyſhop, and Byſhop of the dioceſſe, and by ſpeciall exemption and priueledge from Rome, were vnder the gouernement and ordre of the Abbottes, and Pryours of thoſe religions houſes, which ſayde churches, by colour of the ſayde exemptious, be nowe of ſpeciall graunt from Kyng Henry, &amp; Kyng Edwarde, vnder the rule and gouernement, and iuriſdiction of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall and laye men, who can no more enioye, that ſupremacye, ouer thoſe particuler churches, then the king might ouer the hole realme.</p>
            <p>Be it therfore enacted, that all Archbyſhoppes, and Byſhoppes in their dioceſſes, and al other ſpirituall perſon and perſones, hauynge iuriſdiction, and their miniſters and officers, and no laye perſone, or perſones in euery Churche and place, within the precinct of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, beyng exempt, or not exempte may freely, and without impedime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, execute their ſpirituall iuriſdictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in al pointes &amp; articles, as though no ſuche exemption or graunt had neuer bene made.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaye, and be it enacted, that this acte extende not to take awaye, or diminiſhe the priuileges of the vniuerſities of Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brydge and Oxforde, ne the priuileges, or prerogatiues graunted heretofore to the churches of Weſtminſter, and Wyndeſoure, ne the Cower of London, ne preiudiciall to ſuche temporall Lordes and poſſeſſioners in this realme, as by auncient cuſtome haue enioied pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bate of Teſtamentes, of their tenauntes or other.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuche, as after this reconſiliation, and vnitie of this no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble realme, to the body of Chriſtes churche, it is to be truſted, that by the aboundaunce of Goddes mercy, and grace, deuotion ſhall encreſe and growe in the hartes of many Subiectes of this realme, with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to giue and beſtowe their worldly poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, for the reſuſcitating of almoſe, prayer, and example of good lyfe in this realme, to thinte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſuche godly motions and purpoſes ſhoulde be aduaunced.</p>
            <p>Be it therfore enacted by the aucthoritie of this preſent parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t that it ſhalbe lawfull to ſuche as ſhalbe ſeiſed of any manours, landes, tenementes, perſonages tythes, pencions, portions, or other heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamentes, whatſoeuer in fee ſymple, in poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, reuertio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, in their owne rightes, not beyng coppy holde, maye therof make feoffamentes, grauntes, or any other aſſuraunces, or by his laſte will and Teſtament, in wryting, may be queath and geue in fee ſimple, all and euery the ſayd manours, landes, tenementes, perſonages, tithes pencions, porcions, or other hereditamentes, to any ſpirituall bodye politike, or corporate in this realme or dominions of the ſame, nowe erected or founded, or hereafter to be erected or founded, withoute anye lycence of mortmayne therein to be opteyned, or any wrytte of
<pb facs="tcp:150877:22"/>
               <hi>ad quod dampnum</hi> to bee ſued out for the ſame, the actes <hi>de terri ad manuni mortuam non ponendis,</hi> or any other acte or ſtatute, heretofore had or made in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Sauyng to the Lordes of the ſee, all rentes, ſeruices, dewe, or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng out of any of the ſayde lande or tenementes, or hereditame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, ſo to be amortized, as is aforeſayd.</p>
            <p>Prouided alway, that this clauſe of this acte, for geuyng the liber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie of, or for the amortezing of landes or tenementes, ſhall continue for, and durynge the ſpace of .xx. yeares nexte, and immediatelye fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowinge, and no lenger.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuche, as we your maieſties humble and obedient ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes, the lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and commons in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parliament aſſembled, neither by the makyng, or deliueryng of either the ſupplications aforeſayde, nor by anye clauſe, article, or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence therof, or of any other clauſe article, or ſentence of this, or anye other Statute, or any of the preambles of the ſame, made, or agreed vpon in this ſeſſion of this preſent parliament, by any maner of inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation, conſtruction, implication, or otherwiſe intende to derogate empaire, or diminiſhe any of the prerogatiues, liberties, fraunchiſies preheminences, or iuriſdictions of youre Croune Imperiall of thys realme, and other the dominions to the ſame belongyng: we do moſt humbly beſeche your maieſties, that it may bee declared, and ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and be it enacted and declared by aucthoritie of this preſent par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, that neither the makyng, exhibityng, or inſertinge, in thys preſent ſtatute, or in the preambles of the ſame, of the ſupplications, or promis aforeſayd, or either of them, nor any other thinge or thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, wordes, ſentences, clauſes or articles in the preambles, or body of the actes aforeſayd, ſhalbe conſtrued, vnderſtanded, or expounded, to derogate, diminiſhe or take awaye any the liberties, priuileges, pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rogatiues, preheminences, aucthorities, or iuriſdictions, or any part or parcell therof, which were in your Imperial croune of this realme, or dyd belong to your ſayd Imperiall croune the twenti yeare of the reigne of yours the Queenes maieſties moſt noble father, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your moſt noble progenitours, before the ſayd twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie yere. And the Popes holineſſe, and Sea Apoſtolike, to be reſtored, and to haue and enioye ſuch aucthoritie, preheminence, and iuriſdiction, as hys holineſſe, vſed, and exerciſed, or might lawfully haue vſed and exerci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed by aucthoritie of his ſupremacie, the ſaid twe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tie yere of the reigne of the Kynge your father, within this your realme of Englande, and other your Dominions, without diminution, or enlargement of the ſame, and none other. And the Eccleſiaſticall iuriſdiction of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chebiſhoppes, Biſhoppes, and Ordinaries, to be in the ſame ſtate, for proceſſe of ſuites, puniſhmente of crimes, and execution of cenſures of the churche, with knowledge of cauſes belonging to the ſame, and
<pb n="xxiiii" facs="tcp:150877:22"/>as large in theſe poyntes, as the ſayd iuriſdiction was the ſayde .xx. yeare.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayde, that in and vpon euery ſuch gyftes and deuyſes, to be made to ſuche ſpirituall corporacions, or perſons, as is aforeſayde, the donour, feof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, or deuiſor therof may reſerue to hym, and to his heires for euer, a tenure in franke almayne, or a tenure by diuyne ſeruice: And to haue all remedies and actions, for and vpon the ſayde gyftes, or deuyſes, and tenures, in lyke maner &amp; forme, as was vſed before the eſtatute of Weſtminſter thyrde (commonlye called) <hi>Quia emptores terrarum.</hi> The ſayde eſtatute, or any other lawe or cuſtome nowe beyng, to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary in any wiſe notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes and be it enacted, that all, and euery perſone &amp; perſones, and bodyes polytyke and corporate, whiche nowe haue or hereafter ſhall haue any eſtate of inheritaunce, freholde, terme, or intreſt, of, in, or to any portion, pention, tithes, gleblandes, or other ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall or ſpirituall profytte, whyche by this acte, and lettres of dipenſation rehearſed in the ſame, be permytted &amp; ſuffred to remaine and continue in laye mens poſſeſſions, ſhall &amp; maye haue like remedie for the recouery of the ſame, and euery parte therof, as they, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of them myght haue had before the fyrſte day of this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, Any thing in this act conteyned to the contrary in any wyſe notwithſtandyng.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An Acte for the punyſhment of traiterous wordes againſt the Queenes maieſtie.</head>
            <head type="sub">¶ The .ix. Chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Oraſmuch as nowe of late diuerſe noughty ſedicious malicious, &amp; heretical perſons, not hauing the feare of god before their eyes but in a deuillyſhe ſort, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the duetie of their allegiaunce, haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregated the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues together in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenticles, in diuerſe &amp; ſondry pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phaue places within this citie of Lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>don, eſteming the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes to be in the true faith, where in dede they are in errours &amp; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, &amp; out of the true trade of Chriſtes catholike religion, and in the ſame places at ſeuerall tymes, vſyng theyr phantaſticall and ſciſmati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>call ſeruices, lately taken awaye, and abolyſhed by aucthoritie of Par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liament, haue of theyr moſt malycious &amp; cankerde ſtomakes, prayed agaynſt the Queenes maieſtie, that God would turne her hert from Idolatry to the true fayth, or ells to ſhortene her dayes, or take her quickely out of the way: which prayer was neuer hearde nor redde to haue bene vſed by anye good Chriſtian manne, agaynſte anye
<pb facs="tcp:150877:23"/>Prince though he were a pagan, and infidele, and much leſſe agaynſt any chriſtian Prince, and eſpecially ſo vertuous a Princes as our ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraygne Lady that nowe is knowen to be, whoſe faith is, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes hath bene moſt true and catholique, and conſonaunt and agre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing with Chriſtes catholique church, throughout the worlde diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
            <p>For reformation wherof, be it enacted by thauctoritie of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent parliament, that euery ſuch perſon and perſons, which ſence the beginning of this preſent parliament, haue by expreſſe wordes and ſayinges, prayed, required, or deſyred, as is aforeſayde, or hereafter ſhall pray, by expreſſe wordes or ſayinges, that God ſhoulde ſhorten her dayes, or take her out of the way (whoſe lyfe almighty God long preſerue) or any ſuche lyke malicious prayer amounting to the ſame effect, their procurers and abbettours therin, ſhalbe taken, reputed, and iudged traytours, and euery ſuch praying, requiringe, or deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge ſhalbe iudged, taken, and reputed hygh treaſon, and the offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dours therin, their procurers and abbettours, beyng thereof lauful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conuicte, according to the lawes of this realme, ſhall haue, ſuffre, and forteyte, as in caſes of high treaſon.</p>
            <p>¶ Prouided alway, and be it enacted, that yf any perſon or perſones ſhall be indicted for any the offences aforeſayd, done and perpetrated duryng this ſeſſion of this preſent parliament, and vpon his or their arreignement, ſhal ſhew him or them ſelues penitent for their offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and ſubmite hym or them ſelues, to the kynge and Queenes mercy, and humbly deſyre the ſame, before ſuche Iuſtices or commiſſioners, before whome he or they ſhalbe arraigned, that then no iudgemente of conuiction or attayndour of treaſon, ſhalbe gyuen agaynſt any ſuch perſon or perſons, ſo being penitent, and ſubmitting them ſelues, as is aforeſayde. And in euery ſuche caſe, the iuſtices or commiſſioners, before whom ſuche perſon or perſons ſhalbe arrayned, ſhall haue au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoritie by vertue of this acte, to preſcribe, adiudge, and appoynte, ſuche corporall puniſhment, other then death, to ſuche offender and offenders, as to them by their diſcretion ſhall ſeme conuenient, and vpon that penaunce preſcribed and done, to be diſcharged of the ſaid treaſon, compriſed in that inditement.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An acte wherby certayne offences be made treaſons, and alſo for the gouernement of the kynges and queenes Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties iſſue.</head>
            <head type="sub">¶ The .x. Chapiter.</head>
            <pb n="xxv" facs="tcp:150877:23"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuche as the great mercye and clemencie hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore declared by the Queenes hyghneſſe in releaſynge the penall lawes, made by her progenitours, hath gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen occaſion to many cankard and traiterous hartes, to ymagine, practiſe, and attempt thinges, ſtirring the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to diſobedience and rebellion againſt her highnes co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon pollicy, and duetie of ſubiectes, require that ſome lawe be eſtſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes eſtablyſhed to reſtraine the malyce of ſuch wicked and euill doers, wher by they may be prehibited to blowe abroade ſuch ſhameful ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ders and lyes, as they daylye inuente and imagine of her hyghneſſe, and the kynges maieſtie her mooſte lawefull huſbande, whiche when they bee harde, can not be but odible, and deteſted of al good men, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyderinge they touche their maieſties, vppon whome dependeth the whole vnitie, and vniuerſall welthe of this realme.</p>
            <p>In conſideration wherof be it ordeyned and enacted by the kynge and the queenes maieſties, with thaſſente of the lordes ſpiritual and temporall, and of the commons in this preſent parliament aſſembled and by thauctoritie of the ſame, that if any perſon or perſons after the fyrſt day of February next to come during the marryage betwene the king &amp; the queenes maieſties, do compaſe or ymagine to depriue the kinges maieſtie, that nowe is, from the hauinge &amp; inioyinge ioynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly together with the Queenes hyghnes the ſtile, honoure, and kingly name of the realmes and dominions vnto our ſayde ſoueraygne Lady the queenes highnes appertaynyng, or to deſtroye the kyng that now is, duryng the ſayd matrimonye, or to deſtroye the queenes maieſtie, that nowe is, or the heires of her bodye begotten, beinge kynges or Queenes of this Realme, or to leauye warre within this Realme of England, or within any of the marches of the ſame, agaynſte the kynges maieſtie, that now is, duryng the ſayde maryage, or ageynſte the queenes maieſtie, that nowe is, or any of her ſayd heyres, beyng kynges or queenes of this Realme, or to depoſe the queenes maieſtie that nowe is, or the heires of her bodye begotten, beynge kynges or queenes of this realme, from the Imperiall crowne of the Realmes and dominions aboueſaid. And the ſame compaſſes, or imaginations, or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maliciouſly, aduiſedly, and directly, ſhall or do vtter by open preachyng, expreſſe wordes, or ſayinges or if any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons after the ſaid firſt day of Februarye by preaching expreſſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des or ſayinges, ſhall maliciouſly, aduiſedly, and directly ſaye, pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhe, declare, maintayne, or holde opinion, that the kynges maieſtie, that nowe is, duryng the ſaid matrimony ought not to haue or inioye, ioyntely togither with the queenes maieſtie, the ſtyle, honoure, and kyngly name of this realme, or that any perſon or perſons, being ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the kynge or the queenes maieſties that nowe are, durynge the ſayde matrimony betwene them, ought to haue or enioye the ſtyle, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure,
<pb facs="tcp:150877:24"/>and kyngely name of this realme, or that the Queenes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, that now is, duryng her life, is not, or of ryght ought not to be queene of this realme, or after her death, that the heires of her hygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes body beyng kynges or queenes of this realme, of ryght ought not to be kynges or queenes of this realme, or to haue and enioye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, or that any perſon or perſons, other then the queenes maieſtie, that nowe is, during her life, ought to be queene of this realme, or after her death other then the heires of her body beyng kynges or queenes of this realme, as longe as any of her ſayd heires of her bodye begotten, ſhalbe in lyfe, of ryght ought to haue and enioye the imperiall crowne of this realme. That then euery ſuch offendour, beyng therof duely conuicted, or attaynted by the lawes of this realme, their abbettours, procurers, and counſellours, and all, and euery theyr comforters, knowynge the ſayde offences, or any of theym to bee done, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge therof conuycted or attaynted, as is aboueſayd, for his or their ſuch offence, ſhall forfayte and loſe to the queenes highnes, her heires and ſucceſſours, all his and their goodes, and cattels, and the whole yſſues and profyttes of his and their landes, tenementes, and other hereditamentes, for terme of the lyfe of euery ſuche offendoure or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendours, and alſo ſhal haue, and ſuffer, duryng his and their liues per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>petuall impriſonment.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, and be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayd, that all, and euery eccleſiaſticall perſon, beynge conuicted or attainted in fourme aforeſaid, for euery ſuch his offence, ſhalbe depriued by the ordinary from his promotion ſpirituall or eccleſiaſticall, in ſuche lyke maner and forme; that it ſhalbe lawfull for euery patrone, founder, or giuer therof, to preſent, after ſuch depriuation had, ſome one other to the ſame, as thoughe the ſaid offendour or offendours were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſſed. And if any perſon or perſons beyng hereafter connycted, or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taynted of any the ſayd offences, in fourme aforeſayd committed, ſhal after his or their conniction, or attainder, eftſones committe or perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate any of the ſaid offences in fourme aforeſaid: That then euery ſuche ſeconde offence or offences ſhalbe demed, and adiudged hyghe treaſon, and the offendour or offendours therin, theyr abbettoures, proturers and councellours, and al, and euery their aydours, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forters, knowyng the ſaid offences, or any of them to be done, beyng therof conuicted or attaynted, accordynge to the lawes and ſtatutes of this realme, ſhalbe iudged, and demed highe traytours, and ſhall ſuffer peynes of death, and looſe and forfayte al their goodes, and cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels landes, and tenementes, to the queenes maieſtie, her heires, and ſucceſſours, as in caſes of high treaſon, by the lawes of this realme at this day of right ought to be loſt and forfeyted.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the ſayd aucthoritie, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> if any perſon or perſons at any time after the ſaid fyrſt day of February next to come,
<pb n="xxvi" facs="tcp:150877:24"/>duryng the ſayde marryage, compaſſe, or ymagine the death of the kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges maieſtie, that nowe is, and the ſame maliciouſly, aduyſedly and di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rectly ſhall vtter and attempte by any wrytynge printynge, ouert dede or act, or yf any perſon or perſons at any tyme after the ſaid fyrſt day of February next commynge, ſhal malitiouſly, aduyſedly, and directly, by wrytyng, pryntyng, ouert dede, or act, affirme that the kynges ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, that now is, duryng the ſayd matrimonie, ought not to haue, or enioy ioyntly togethers with the queenes hyghnes, the ſtyle, honoure and kyngly name of this realme, or that any perſon or perſons, beynge neyther the kyng, or the Queenes maieſtie, that nowe is, durynge the ſaid matrimonie betwene them ought to haue or enioye the ſtyle, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and kyngly name of this realme. Or yf any perſon or perſons, after the ſayd day, by any wrytyng, pryntyng, ouert dede, or acte, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly, aduiſedly, and directly, do affirme, that the queenes maieſtie that nowe is, duryng her lyfe, is not, or ought not to be queene of this realme, or after her death, that the heyres of her hyghnes body being kynges or queenes of this realme, of right ought not to haue and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioy the Imperiall crowne of this realme, or that anye perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons other then the queenes maieſtie, that nowe is, durynge her lyfe, or after her death, other then the heyres of her body begotten, being kynges or queenes of this realme, as longe as any of her ſayde heyres of her body ſhalbe in lyfe, of ryght ought to haue and enioye the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall crowne of this realme. That then euery ſuche offence and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences ſhalbe adiudged hygh treaſon, &amp; the offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der &amp; offenders there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, theyr abbettours, procurers, &amp; councellers, and al, and euery their aydours, and comforters, knowing the ſayd offences, or any of them to be done, beinge therof conuicted, or attaynted by the lawes and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes of this realme, ſhalbe demed and adiudged hygh traytours, and ſhal ſuffer paynes of death, and looſe and forfayt all theyr goodes, and cattels, landes, and tenementes to the Queenes maieſtie, her heyres and ſucceſſours as in caſes of hygh treaſon, as is aboue ſayde.</p>
            <p>And albeit we the Lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons in this preſent parliament aſſembled, haue firme hope and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in the goodnes of Almyghty God, that lyke as he hath hether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to myraculouſly preſerued the queenes maieſtie from many great and imminent perils and daungers, euen ſo he wyll of his infinite goodnes gyue her hyghnes ſtrength, the rather by oure continuall prayers, to paſſe well the daunger of deliueraunce of chylde, wherewith it hathe pleaſed hym, (to all our greate comfortes, to bleſſe her. Yet foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as all thynges of this worlde be vncerteyne, and hauynge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes the dolorous experience of the inconſtant gouernemente durynge the tyme of the reigne of the late kynge, Edwarde the ſyxte, do playnely ſee the manyfolde inconueniences, greate daungers, and peryls, that may enſue to this hole realme, yf foreſyght be not vſed
<pb facs="tcp:150877:25"/>to preuent euyll chaunces, yf they ſhulde happen. For the eſchewynge wherof, we the Lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and the commons in this preſent parliament aſſembled, for, and in conſideration of a moſt ſpecial truſt and confidence, that we haue, and repoſe in the kinges ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ieſtie, for, and concernyng the good and polityke gouernement, ordre, and adminiſtration of this realme in the tyme of the yonge yeares of the iſſue or iſſues of her maieſties body to be borne, if it ſhulde pleaſe God to call the Quenes highnes out of this preſent lyfe, duringe the tender yeares of ſuche iſſue or iſſues (which God for bidde) according to ſuche order and maner, as hereafter in this preſent acte, his hygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes moſt gratious pleaſure is ſhulde be declared and ſette forth, haue made our moſte humble ſuite by thaſſent of the Quenes highnes, that his maieſtie would voucheſafe to accepte and take vpon hym the rule, ordre, education, and gouernement of the ſayd iſſue oriſſues to bee borne, as is aforeſayd, vpon which our ſuite being of his ſayd maieſtie moſte graciouſly accepted. It hath pleaſed his highnes not onely to declare, that like as for the fyrſt part his maieſtie verely truſteth, that almyghtie God (who hath hitherto preſerued the queenes maieſtie) to giue this realme ſo good an hope of certeyne ſucceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the bluo roial of the ſame realme, wil aſſiſt her highnes with his graces &amp; benedicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to ſee the fruite of her body wel brought forth, liue, and able to gouerne, wherof neither al this realme ne al the worlde beſides ſhuld, or coulde receaue more comforte, then his maieſtie ſhulde and woulde. Yet yf ſuch chaunce ſhulde happen, his maieſtie at our humble deſires is pleaſed and contented, not alonely to accepte and take vpon him the cure and charge of the education, rule, ordre, and gouernement of ſuch iſſues, as of this moſt happy mariage ſhalbe borne betwene the quee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes highnes and him, but alſo duryng the tyme of ſuch gouernement, wold by all wayes and meanes ſtudy, trauayle, and imploye him ſelfe to aduaunce the weale, both publique and priuate of this realme, and dominions there vnto belongyng, accordyng to the ſayd truſte in hys maieſtie repoſed, with no leſſe good wyll and affection, then yf hys hyghnes had byn naturally borne amongeſt vs.</p>
            <p>In conſideration wherof beit enacted by the kynge and the quee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes moſt excellent maieſties, by thaſſent of the Lordes ſpiritual and temporall, and the commons of this preſent Parlyament aſſembled, and by thaucthoritie of the ſame that if it ſhal ſo pleaſe God, to call the queenes maieſtie out of this preſent lyfe, whiche god forbidde, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the iſſue of her bodye, inheritable to the crowne of this realme, yf it be male, ſhall accomplyſhe the age of .xviii yeares, or if it be female, before it ſhalbe of the age of .xv. yeares, and not maried, after the age of conſent, and before the ſaid age of .xv. yeares: That then and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly after, and from the deceaſſe of our ſayd Soueraigne Ladye the queene, the kinges maieſty, that now is, ſhal haue the rule, order, edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,
<pb n="xxvii" facs="tcp:150877:25"/>and gouernemente of the perſone of ſuche iſſue, or iſſues, and the rule, ordre, and gouernement (vnder ſuche iſſue, or iſſues) of this realme, and the dominions to the ſame belongyng, vntill theſame iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, or iſſues, inheritable to the Imperiall croune of this realme, if it bee male, ſhall accompliſhe the full age of eightene yeres and if it bee female, vntill ſuche iſſue female, ſhall accompliſhe the age of fiuetene yeres, and be maried after the age of conſent, and before theſaied age of fiuetene yeres, if the ſaide iſſue or iſſues, and oure ſaide ſoueraigne Lorde the Kyng, ſhall ſo long liue together: and that duryng, and by all the tyme of ſuche gouernemente, all, and euery the pactes, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauntes, articles, and agrementes, mencioned and compreſed in the treatiſes, and acte of Parliament, and euery of them made, and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cluded, for, and concernynge the honourable mariage, hade and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mate, betwene the Kynge and Quenes Maieſties, whiche on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of his Maieſtie, been to be obſerued, perfourmed and kepte, ſhal after the deceaſſe of the Quenes Maieſtie, durynge the tyme of the ſaid gouernement, remain, continue, and be in as good, and full force ſtrength, and effecte, to all intentes, and purpoſes, as thei were at a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tyme, durynge the ſaied Mariage, or now been, and as if they were newly by apte woordes, termes, and ſentences, inſerted and reherſed in this preſente Act, and newly made and enacted, to ſtand, remain, continue, and to bee obſerued, and kepte, duryng the tyme of the ſaied gouernemente, and ſhalbe by his Maieſtie, duryng the ſaied tyme in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiolably obſerued perfourmed, mainteined, and vpholden, in ſuche ſorte, and in as full large, and ample maner, to all reſpectes, as thei ſhoulde, and ought to be, duryng the tyme of the ſaid marriage, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: and his highnes, and the Queenes moſte excellente Maieſtie, are pleaſed and contented, that it be enacted by this preſent Parliament that nothinge ſhalbe doone, permitted, or aſſented vnto by his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie to the contrary.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted, by the aucthoritie aforeſaid, that if any perſone or perſons, duryng the tyme that our ſaied ſoueraigne lorde the Kynge that now is, ſhall, and ought to haue the ordre, rule, educa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion, &amp; gouernement of ſuche iſſue, or iſſues, beynge, Kynge or Quene of this realme, accordynge to the ordre and prouiſion aforeſaied, mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly, aduiſedly, and derectly, by writing, printing, ouerte dede, or acte, dooe compaſſe, attempte, and go aboute to deſtroye the perſone of our ſaied ſoueraigne lorde, or to depriue, or remoue his ſaied high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, from the order rule, educacion, and gouernemente of the ſame iſſue, or iſſues, beynge Kyng or Quene of this realme, contrary to the tenour, entente, and true meaning of this preſent acte: that then eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuche perſon or perſones ſo offendynge, their procurers and abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, beeyng therof lawfully conuicte or attainted by the lawes of this realme, ſhalbee demed and adiuged high Traitours: And that
<pb facs="tcp:150877:26"/>all and euery ſuche offence and offences, ſhalbe demed and adiuged hyghe treaſon: And the offendour and offendours therein, their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curers, counſaylours, and abettours, ſhall incurre the daungers, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faytures, and penalties of hygh treaſon.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by thauctoritie afore ſayd, that al trials hereafter to be had, awarded, or made, for any treaſon, ſhalbe had, &amp; vſed onely, according to the due order and courſe of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon lawes of this realme, and not otherwyſe: Sauyng to euery perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones, bodyes polytyke and corporate, theirheyres, and ſucceſſoures other then the offendours, and their heyres, and ſuch perſone &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones, as clayme to anye of their vſes, al ſuche rightes, titles, intereſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, poſſeſſions, leaſſes, rentes, reuertions, offices, and other profites whiche they, or anye of them ſhall haue at the daye of the commiting ſuche treaſons, or at any tyme afore, in as large and ample maner, as if this acte had neuer bene had nor made.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it declared and enacted by thaucthori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie aforeſayd, that conceylement, or kepyng ſecrete of any hygh trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, be demed and taken onely, miſpriſion of treaſon, &amp; the offenders therein to forfayte and ſuffer, as in caſes of miſpriſion of treaſon hath heretofore bene vſed. Any thing aboue mencioned to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrarynot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alſo, that if it ſhall fortune hereafter any of the peares of this realme, to be indicted of any of the offences made treaſon, or mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpriſion of treaſon by this acte, that then the ſame peares, or peare, ſo beynge indected, ſhalbe putte to aunſwere vnto euery ſuche endicte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, before the highe ſtewarde of Englande for the tyme beyng, and to haue his and their triall by his and theyr peares, and to receaue and haue ſuch like iudgement vpon theſame tryal of his or their pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, or making open confeſſion of the ſame offence, or offences, as is vſed in other caſes of hygh treaſon.</p>
            <p>And it is further enacted by thauctoritie aforeſayde, that no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone or perſones ſhall in any wyſe be impeched for any of the offences aboue ſayde, committed onely by open preachyng, or wordes, onleſſe the offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der or offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders be therof indectedwithin ſyxe monethes next after the ſame open preachyng or wordes. Anye thyng conteyned in this acte to the contrary notwithſtandyng.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayde that vpon thearraygnement of any perſone, which hereafter ſhal for tune to be arraygned for any treaſon, mentioned in this acte, all, and euery ſuche perſon &amp; perſones, or two of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the leaſt, as ſhal here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after wryte, declare, confeſſe, or depoſe any thyng or thnges againſt the perſon to be arrayned, ſhall, if they be then lyuing, and within the, realme be brought forth in perſon before the partie arraygned, if he requyre the ſame, and obiecte, and ſaye openly in his hearyng, what
<pb n="xxviii" facs="tcp:150877:26"/>they or any of them can agaynſt him, for, or concernyng any the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, contained in the indictement, where vpon the partie ſhalbe ſo ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raigned, onleſſe the partie arraygned for any ſuch treaſon, ſhall wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyngly confeſſe the ſame at the tyme of his or their arraygnement.</p>
            <p>Prouided neuertheleſſe, and be it enacted by thauctoritie afore ſaid that in all caſes of high treaſon, concernyng coyne curraunt within this realme, or for counterfeyting the Kyng or Queenes ſignet, pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie ſeale, great ſeale, or ſigne manuell, ſuche maner of triall, and none other be obſerued and kept, as heretofore hath bene vſed by the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon lawes of this realme. Any lawe, ſtatute, or any other thynge or thinges to the contrary notwithſtanding.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, that the councellours, procurers, comforters, and abbettours for his or their firſt offence ſhal ſuffer like puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, penaltie, and forfayture, as is conteyned in this acte againſt the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall offendours for theyr firſt offence, and none other. And that the counſellours, procurers, comforters, and abbettours, for his or their ſeconde offence ſhall ſuſtayne lyke punyſhment, penaltie, &amp; forfaiture as is conteyned in this acte agaynſt the principall offendour or offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours for their ſecond offence, and none other.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An Acte for the puniſhment of bringing in of counterfeyte coyne of forrayne realmes, being curraunt within this realme.</head>
            <head type="sub">¶ The .xi. Chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here diuerſe and ſondrye coynes of golde and ſyluer of other realmes, not beynge of the propre coyne of thys realme of Englande, and yet by the ſufferaunce and conſent of the kyng and queene our Soueraigne Lord and Lady, be curraunt in payment within this realine many, yl diſpoſed perſones for their owne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupte lucre &amp; aduau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage, haue nowe of late brought into this realme, from the parties of beyonde the ſea, great quantitie of forged &amp; cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeyte money, lyke to the ſayd coyne of other forreyne realmes, and haue vttered the ſame here by marchaundyſing, and otherwyſe to diuerſe of the ſubiectes of this realme, to their great deceyte, hurte, and dammage, becauſe the ſayde yll diſpoſed perſones haue percea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and vnderſtanded, that there was not, nor yet is anye ſufficiente lawe or ſtatute made or prouided for the condigne puniſhment of the offendours in that behalfe.</p>
            <p>Wherfore be it enacted and eſtabliſhed by the aucthoritie of thys preſente Parliamente, that yf anye perſone or perſones, after the xx. daye of Ianuary nexte commynge, ſhallbryng from the partyes
<pb facs="tcp:150877:27"/>of beyond the ſea into this realme, or into anye the dominions of the ſame any ſuch falſe and counterfeyt coyne or money, beyng curraunt within this realme as is aforeſayde, knowyng the ſame coyne or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to be falſe and counterfeyte, to thintent to vtter, or make payme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with the ſame within this realme, or any the dominions of the ſame, by marchaundyſing, or otherwiſe, that all, and euery ſuche perſon or perſons ſo offendyng, as is aforeſayde, their counſaylours, procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, aydours, and abbettors in that behalfe, ſhalbe demed and iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to be offendours in highe treaſon, and ſhall ſuffer after lawefull conuiction or atteynder therof, ſuche paynes of death, loſſe and forfai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture of landes, goodes, and cattelles, as other offendours ſhall do, in caſes of highe treaſon.</p>
            <p>And be it further enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſayd, that al, and euery perſon and perſones, that ſhall at any tyme after the ſayde .xx. day of Ianuary, be accuſed or impeched of any of the offences, contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and prouided for in this eſtatute, or of any other offence or offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, concernyng the impayryng, counterfeytyng, or forgyng of anye coyne curraunte within this realme, ſhall, and maye be endicted, ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reyned, tryed, conuicted, or atteynted by ſuch like euidence, and in ſuche maner and forme, as hath bene vſed &amp; accuſtomed within thys realme, at any tyme before the firſt yeare of the raigne of our late ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne lorde kyng Edwarde the ſixt. Any ſtatute, cuſtome, lawe, or vſage to the contrary therof in any wiſe, notwithſtanding.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An Acte for the impounding of diſtreſſes.</head>
            <head type="sub">¶ The .xii. Chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or the auoydinge of greuous vexations, exactions, troubles, and diſorder in takyng of diſtreſſes, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding of cattel, be it enacted by aucthoritie of this preſent Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that from, and after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt dai of Apryl next co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, no diſtreſſe of cattell ſhalbe dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen out of the hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred, rape, wapentake, or lath, where ſuch diſtreſſe is, or ſhalbe taken, except it be to a pounde, ouerte with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſayd ſhire, not aboue three myles diſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, from the place where the ſaid diſtreſſe is, taken, and that no cattel, or other goodes diſtrei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, or taken by waye of diſtreſſe, for any maner of cauſe, at one time ſhalbe impounded in ſeuerall places, wherby the owner or owners of ſuch diſtreſſe ſhalbe conſtrayned to ſue ſeuerall repleuis for the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie of the ſayd diſtreſſe, ſo taken at one tyme, vpon payne euery per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon, offending contrary to this acte, ſhal forfeyte to the partie greued for euery ſuch offence a hundred ſhillinges, and treble damages.</p>
            <p>And further be it enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayde, that after
<pb n="xxix" facs="tcp:150877:27"/>the ſayd fyrſt day of Apryl, no perſon or perſons ſhal take for kepyng in pounde, impoundyng, or poundage of any maner of diſtreſſe, aboue the ſomme of .iiii. pence for any one whole diſtreſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhalbe ſo impoun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded, and where leſſe hath ben vſed there to take leſſe, vpon the payne of fyue pounde to be payd to the party greued, ouer and beſides ſuche money as he ſhall take, aboue the ſomme of foure pence. Any vſage or preſcription to the contrary in any wyſe notwithſtandynge.</p>
            <p>And for the more ſpedier deliuerye of cattell, taken by waye of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe, it is further enacted by the ſayd aucthoritie, that euerye Shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riffe of ſhires, being no cities, nor townes made ſhyres, ſhal at his firſt countie daye, or within two monethes nexte after he hath receaued his patent of his office of ſhirifwike, ſhall depute, appoynte, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clayme in the ſhyre towne within his baylywike, four deputies at the leaſt, dwellyng not aboue twelue myles, one dyſtaunt from another, which ſayd deputies ſo appoynted and proclaymed, ſhall haue aucto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie in the ſheriffes name to make repleuies, and deliueraunce of ſuch diſtreſſes, in ſuch maner and forme, as the ſheriffe may, or ought to do vpon payne that euery Sheriffe, for euery moneth that he ſhal lacke ſuch deputie or deputies, ſhall forfeyte for euerye ſuche offence fyue poundes, the one halfe of which forfaytures ſhalbe to the kynge and Quenes highnes, her heyres and ſucceſſours, the other halfe to him that wil ſue for the ſame by bil, playnt, information, or action of debt, in any the kyng and quenes courtes of recorde, in which no eſſoygne protection, nor wager of lawe ſhalbe admitted.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An Acte appoynting in order to iuſtices of peace, touchynge the baylement of priſoners.</head>
            <head type="sub">¶ The .xiii. Chapiter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in the parliament holden at Weſtminſter, in the .iii. yeare of the reigne of the noble prynce, kyng Henrye the ſeuenth, it was among other thinges ordeyned and ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, that no priſoner arreſted for felonie, ſhould be letten to bayle or maynepryce, by anye one Iuſtice of peace, but by the hole Iuſtices, or at leaſt by two of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherof one to be of the <hi>Quorum,</hi> Synce the makyng of which eſtatute, one Iuſtice of peace, in the name of him ſelfe and one other of the Iuſtices his compagnion not makyng the ſayd Iuſtice partie nor priuie vnto the caſe, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the priſoner ſhould be bayled, hath often tymes by ſiniſter labor, and meanes, ſet at large the greateſt, and notableſt offenders, ſuche as be not repleuiſably by the lawes of this realme, and yet the rather to hyde their affections in that behalfe, haue ſignified the cauſe of theyr apprehenſion to be put onely for ſuſpition of felony, wherby the
<pb facs="tcp:150877:28"/>ſayd offendours hath eſcaped vnpunyſhed, and do dayly, to the high diſpleaſure of almightie God, the great peryll of the kynge and Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes true ſubiectes, and encoragement of all theues and euill doers.</p>
            <p>For reformation wherof, be it ordeyned and enacted by the kyng and Queenes maieſties, the lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and the commons in this preſent parliament aſſembled, and by aucthoritie of the ſame, that from, and after the fyrſt day of Apryll nexe commyng, no Iuſtice or Iuſtices of peace, ſhall lette to bayle or mainepryce, anye ſuch perſon or perſones, which for any offence or offences, by theym, or any of them committed, be declared not to be repleniſed or bayled, or be forbidden to be repleued, or bayled, by the eſtatute of Weſtmin. prymer, made in the parliamente, holden in the thyrde yeare of the reygne of kynge Edwarde the firſt. And furthermore, that any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſones arreſted for manſtaughter or felonie, or ſuſpection of manſlaughter or ſelonie, beyng bayleable by the lawe, ſhall not after the ſayde fyrſte day of Apryli, be lette to bayle or maynpryſe, by anye Iuſtices of peace, if it be not in open Seſſions, except it be by two Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtices of peace, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt, wherof one to be of the <hi>Quorum,</hi> &amp; the ſame Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtices to be preſent together, at the tyme of the ſaid baylment or main pryce, which baylement or mainpryce they ſhall certefye in wrytinge, ſubſcribed, or ſygned with theyr owne handes, at the nexte generall goale deliuery, to be holden within the countie, where the ſaide per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or perſons ſhalbe arreſted or ſuſpected. And that the ſayde Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices, or one of them being of the <hi>Quorum</hi> when any ſuche pryſoner is brought before them, for anye manſlaughter or felonye, before anye baylement or maynepryſe, ſhall take the examination of the ſayd pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, and information of them that brynges him, of the facte, and cir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cumſtaunces therof, and the ſame, or aſmuth therof, as ſhalbe materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to proue the felonye, ſhall put in wrytinge before they make the ſame baylement, whiche ſayd examination together, with the ſayde baylement, the ſayd Iuſtices ſhal certifye at the next generall goale delyuerye, to be holden within the limittes of theyr commiſſion, and that euery Coroner, vpon any inquiſition before hym founde, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by any perſon or perſons ſhalbe indicted for murder, or ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſſaughter, or as acceſſary, or acceſſaries to the ſame, before the muther or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaughter committed, ſhall put in writinge the effecte of the euidence, geuen to the Iurye before hym, beyng materiall, and afwell the ſaid Iuſtices, as the ſayd Coroner, ſhall haue aucthoritie by thys acte, to binde al ſuch by recongniſaunce, or obligation, as do beclare any thing materiall, to proue the ſayd murder or manfiaughter, offences, or fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonies, or to be acceſſary, or acceſſaries to the ſame, as is aforeſayd to appeare at the next genarall goale deliuerye, to be holden within the Countie, citie, or towne corporate, where the triall therof ſhalbe, then and there to geue euidence agaynſt the partie ſo indicted, at the tyme
<pb n="xxx" facs="tcp:150877:28"/>of his triall, and ſhall certifye aſwell the ſame euydence, as ſuch bond and bondes in wryting, as he ſhall take together, with the inquiſition or indictment before him taken and founde, at, or before the tyme, of his ſayd tryall therof, to be had or made. And lykewyſe, the ſayd Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices ſhall certifye all and euery ſuche bonde, taken before theym, in lyke maner as before is ſayd of baylementes and examination. And in caſe any Iuſtice of peace, or <hi>Quorum,</hi> or Coroner, ſhall after the ſayde fyrſt day of Apryll, offende in any thing contrary to the true intente, and meaning of this preſent acte: That then the Iuſtices of gaole de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyuery, of the Shire, citie, towne, or place, where ſuche offence ſhall happen to be committed, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> due profe therof, by examination before them ſhall for euery ſuch offence, ſet ſuche fyne on euerye of the ſame Iuſtices of peace, and Coroner, as the ſame Iuſtices of gaole deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhall thynke mete, and ſhall eſtrte the ſame as other fynes and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merciamentes aſſeſſed before Iuſtices of gaole deliuery ought to be.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwaies, and be it further enacted by thauctoritie afore ſaid, that Iuſtices of peace, and Coroners within the citie of London and the countie of Middelſex, and in other cities, boroughes, &amp; tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes corporate within this realme, and Wales, ſhall within theyr ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall iuriſdictions, haue aucthoritie to let to Bayle, fellous and pryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, in ſuch maner and fourme as they haue bene heretofore accuſio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med, this acte or any thing therein conteined, to the contrarye not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding. And alſo ſhall take examinations, and bondes, as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſayd, vpon euery baylement by them or any of them to be made, and ſhall certifye euery ſuch baylementes bondes, and examinations by them or any of them, taken or made at the next gaole delyuerye to be holden within the ſhyre, citie, borough, or towne, where theyr ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall iuriſdictions extendeth, vpon lyke payne and forfayture, as is before lymitted in this preſent acte.</p>
            <p>And be it alſo enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſaid, that no writtes of <hi>Habeas corpus,</hi> or <hi>Certiorary,</hi> ſhalbe hereafter graunted, to remoue anye pryſoner out of any gaole, or to remoue anye recogniſaunce, excepte the ſame writtes be ſigned with the propre handes of the chiefe Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, or in his abſence, one of the Iuſtices of the courte, out of whiche the ſame writtes ſhalbe awarded, or made, vpon payne that he that writeth any ſuche wryttes, not beyng ſygned as is aforeſayd, to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayte to our ſayd ſoueraygne lorde the kyng and the quene, for euery ſuch wrytte and wryttes, fyue poundes.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An acte for the makyng of ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, and fuſtian of Naples in Norwiche.</head>
            <head type="sub">¶ The .xiiii. Chapter.</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:150877:29"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here of late yeares paſſed, Ruſſels called Ruſſels Sat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tens, and Sattens reuerſes, haue bene practiſed to be made beyond the ſeas of the wolles, bredde in the coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie of Norfolke, and by reaſon therof, ſo great quantite of the ſayde Ruſſels Sattens, and Sattens Reuerſes haue ben brought into this realme, ſold, &amp; worne aſwell in euery parte of this realme, as in the partes beyonde the ſeas, that thereby the myſteries of Worſtedes makynge, and weuyng, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by marchauntes, and inhabitauntes of the citie of Norwiche, haue heretofore ben well maynteyned and relieued, is now at this preſent almooſt wholy decayed and brought out of eſtimation, and very lyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle worne, either within this realme, or in any other forreine realms, to the greate hynderaunce, and decay of the ſayde citie, and Citezins of the ſame citie. For remedye wherof Thomas Marſham Maiour of the citie of Norwyche, Iohn Corbet Eſquier, Auſten Stewarde, Robert Leche, Robert Rugge, Iohn Ball, and Alexander Mather Aldermen of the ſayd citie. Thomas Whall, Thomas Pecke, Raphe Marſham, Robert Henry, Iohn Sutton, Rycharde Tomſon, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tezins, and marchauntes of the ſayd Citie, at theyr great coſtes and charges, aſwel in brynging of certayn ſtrangers from the partes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yonde the ſeas into the ſayd citie, as alſo in makyng of Lombes, and all other prouiſion for the ſame, and alſo haue called vnto them eyght perſons of the moſt diſcrete and worthy men of the miſterye of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtede weuyng, within the ſayd citie, that is to ſaye, Iohn Cooke, Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes Lyn, Iohn Croſſe, Simon Petit, Iohn Marſhal, Roger Lecke Edmond Barker, and Edmonde Selers, beynge the number of .xxi perſons, which haue not only made Ruſſels Sattens, and Sattens Reuerſes, and fuſtian of Naples within the ſayd citie of Norwich of Norfolke wolles, but alſo haue learned and taughte other citezins &amp; inhabitauntes of the ſayd citie to make the ſame, in ſuch good and per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fect maner, that muche better Ruſſels Sattens, Sattens reuerſes, and fuſtian of Naples, and ſuch lyke, and for eaſyer prices, be nowe at this preſent wrought and made within the ſaid citie, then heretofore hath ben, or nowe be made in anye of the parties beyonde the ſeas, wherby the ſayd citie and inhabitauntes therof, maye, and be lyke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne to be relieued and brought to theyr olde eſtate, to the great ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uauncement of the commodities of this realme, and enrychynge the ſame, yf ſome good and polytyke lawes and ordinaunces were made for the good continuance of the true makynge of the ſayde Ruſſelles Sattens, Sattens Reuerſes, and fuſtian of Naples, and ſuche lyke.</p>
            <p>In conſideration whereof be it enacted by the aſſente of the kynge and queenes hyghnes, the Lordes ſpirituall and temporall, and the commons of this preſent Parliament aſſembled, and by thauctoritie
<pb n="xxxi" facs="tcp:150877:29"/>of the ſame, that the ſaid ruſſels, ſattens and ſattens reuerſes, and fu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian of Naples hereafter to be made onely within the ſayd citie, may from hence forth bere the name, and he called by the name of Norwi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſattens and Norwich fuſſians, and that the Maior and the afore mentioned citezens of the ſame citie, which before this time hath ben at the coſtes and charges of the bringing of the ſayd ſtraungers into the ſame citie, for the making of the ſaid ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes, and fuſtians of Naples, and ſuch the afore mentioned eyght per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that they haue called vnto them, ſhalbe a felowſhyp of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfes, and ſhal yearely the thyrde day of February chooſe of their felowes, foure wardeynes within the Guylde hall of the ſaid citie, or anye o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and conuenient place in the ſame citie, and the ſame war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deynes ſo being chooſen, ſhall ſtand, and be wardens of the ſame fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhyp, duryng one whole yeare, next enſuing the ſaid election &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame wardeynes after the ſayd election, ſhal come before the Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ior of the ſayd citie for the tyme being, yearely the monday next after the ſaide third day of Februarye, and before the ſayde. Maior ſhalbe ſworne diligently to viewe ſearch, and ſee all the ruſſels ſattens, ſat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens reuerſes, and fuſtians of Naples, then made or that ſhalbe made within the ſayd citie, duryng the ſaide yeare. And ſuche of the ſayde ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, &amp; fuſtian of Napels, as ſhal appeare and be demed by them to be lawfully truly &amp; workemanly wrought ſhall ſeale with a ſeale of leade, bearyng the armes of the citie of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>which, wherby it may be knowen to the marchaunt, or buyer of them that the ſame be allowed and truly made.</p>
            <p>And that alſo it may be enacted by the aucthoritie aforeſaid, that the ſaide wardeynes and felowſhyp ſhalbe a body corporate, and to be named and be inabled bi this acte to ſue, and be ſued and to gyue, and to take by the name of wardeynes, and felowſhyppe of the myſterye of ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, and fuſtian of Norwiche making within the ſayd citie of Norwich. And yf any defaulte at any tyme ſhalbe founde in any of the ſayd ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, &amp; fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian of Norwiche, or in any of them by the ſaid wardeynes, that the ſame defauite ſhalbe reformed and the offendour or offendours ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to be punyſhed, according to ſuch rules and ordinaunces, as hereaf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter from time to tyme ſhalbe made within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid citie by the Maior of the ſaid citie for the time being, and by the ſayde foure wardeynes, and the felowſhyppe of the ſayde occcpation or myſtery, or the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt number of the ſayd felowſhyppe, for, and concernynge the ſame, and that the ſame defaultes from time to time, as occaſion ſhal ſerue ſhalbe enquired of, &amp; tried before the Maior of the ſaid citie of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich for the ryme beynge, by the othes of twelue honeſte menne of the foreſayde felowſhyppe. And that the ſayde foure wardeynes ſo chooſen and ſworne, ſhall haue ful power &amp; aucthoritie, to do execute,
<pb facs="tcp:150877:30"/>preſent, and reforme all, and ſinguler thyng and thinges, of, for, and concernyng the ſayd miſtery, makynge, workynge, and occupieng of the ſayd ruſſels ſattens, ſatins reuerſes, &amp; fuſtian of Norwich wyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſayd citie, in ſuche maner and forme, as in, or by the ſayde ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances ſhalbe expreſſed and declared, and that at al tymes hereafter, and from tyme to tyme, it ſhalbe lawfull to the Maior of the ſayd cite for the tyme being, and to the before named felowſhip and wardeyns of the ſame miſtery, and the more part of them, &amp; to their ſucceſſours, to make and ordayne from tyme to tyme, rules, lawes, &amp; ordinaunces mete and neceſſarye for the good ordre &amp; gouernaunce of the ſaid mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, and for the true and wel makyng of the ſaid ruſſels ſattens, ſat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens reuerſes, and fuſtian of Norwiche, and the ſame ordinaunces ſo made, to be at al times obeyed by al thinhabitaunce of the ſaid citie, or ſuburbes of the ſame, and to be put in due executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid maior and wardeyns, and their ſucceſſers for the tyme being, in ſuch maner and forme, as by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ordinaunce ſhalbe ordeined and declared. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch as nowe be, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hereafter ſhalbe makers of the ſaid ruſſels ſat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens, ſattens reuerſes, and fuſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Norwich, and euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> within the ſaid citie, ſhall not fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> henceforth occupye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid miſterye, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd ruſſels ſatte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſattens reuerſes, and fuſtian of Norwi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, nor of any of them within the ſayd citie, by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, or by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, before he or they ſo occupying the ſayd miſterye within the ſayd citie, be made free of the ſayd citie, and admitted to be of the ſaid felow ſhip by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maior of the ſayd citie, and wardeines and felowſhyp of the ſayd miſtery for the time being. And that no perſon do occupie by him ſelfe, or any other for him out of the ſayd citie, the ſayd miſtery of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, and fuſtians of Naples, or of any of them, before he or they ſo occupieng the ſame, haue ben pre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tice to the ſayd miſterye by the terme of ſeuen yeares, or els admytted by the ſaid Maior and felowſhip, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more parte of them, vpon payne of forfaiture of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ruſſels ſatte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſattens reuerſes, and fuſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Nor wiche by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be made contrary to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forme of this act.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes, and be it enacted by thauctoritie aforeſaid, that the ſaid Maior and wardeynes for the time being, ſhall not take anye ſomme of monye, or reward to their owne proper vſes, for the admit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting of any perſon or perſons to occupy the ſayd myſtery, vpon payne of forfayture of treble the value of the reward, or ſomme of mony, ſo by them or any of them to be taken.</p>
            <p>Prouided alſo, that it ſhalbe lauful to the ſaide wardeynes, and to euery of them for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time being, by all waies and meanes, &amp; at all law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful times, dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly from time to time, to make ſearch by dew and ordi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nary wayes, for al maner of the ſaid ruſſels ſattens, ſattens renerſes and fuſtian of Norwiche, that ſhall happen to be founde by them defec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyue, for lacke of good and true workemanſhip. And that it ſhalbe lavo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full
<pb n="xxxii" facs="tcp:150877:30"/>to the ſayd wardeynes &amp; euery of them for the time being by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of this acte, to ſeaſe &amp; take the ſayd ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes, and fuſtian, &amp; bringe and preſent the ſame clothes ſo ſeaſed and ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken, to the Maior of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid citie for the time being, &amp; vnto his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, to thintent that twelue honeſt, lawful, and experte men of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid myſterie, &amp; felowſhip being ſworne before the ſaid Maior, may by ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue of their othes, make inquirie, and preſent the maner of the ſayde defaultes before the ſaid Maior, for the time being accordinge to ſuch good and holſome ordinances &amp; rules, as ſhalbe ordeined and made for the conſeruation &amp; good continuaunce of the ſayd occupation and miſterie, &amp; the true makyng and working of the ſaid ruſſels ſattens, ſattens, reuerſes, &amp; fuſtians of Norwiche. And that al &amp; euery perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and perſons, that ſhall occupy, vſe, &amp; exerciſe the ſaide miſterie, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of the ſaid ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, &amp; fuſtians of Norwi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che, or any of them, contrary to the forme, tenour, playne meaning, &amp; intent of this acte, and of the rules and ordinaunces, that at any time hereafter by aucthoritie of this acte ſhalbe ordeyned &amp; made for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinuaunce of the true &amp; perfect making of the ſayd ruſſels ſattens, ſat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tens reuerſes &amp; fuſtian of Norwiche, ſhal for feyte and looſe for euery tyme ſo offending, or making any ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, &amp; fuſtian of Norwiche, contrarie to the meaning, tenour &amp; effecte of the ſaid acte, rules, and ordinaunces, concerning the ſame, ſuch fines, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merciamentes, &amp; paines as ſhalbe adiudged, aſſeſſed, and affered by twelue experte men of the ſaid felowſhype vpon their othes, the ſame twelue perſons to be ſworne before the ſayd Maior &amp; wardeynes to enquire and make true verdicte, &amp; preſentment of ſuch defaultes, the one halfe of al which forfeyture to be to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maior of the ſaid citie for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time being, &amp; his ſuceeſſors, and thother moitie to the ſaid wardeins for the time being, &amp; their ſucceſſours, by action of dette, bil, playnt, or information in any courte of record, in which action, bil, plaint, or infor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mation no wager of lawe, protection, inuencion, or forren Ple, ſhalbe allowed. And in caſe it ſhall fortune hereafter, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any of the ſaid ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, &amp; fuſtian of Norwich ſhall lacke of ſuch le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thes &amp; bredes, or of the true &amp; enſuing making or ſorting of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yarne as ſhalbe appoynted, &amp; ſet furth by the ſayd rules &amp; ordinaunces, and the ſame ſo to be found defectiue by verdicte of twelue men of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd feloſhyp before the ſayd Maior &amp; wardeins &amp; their ſucceſſors: That then the ſaid ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, &amp; fuſtians of Naples, &amp; euery of them ſo found defectiue, to be cutte in two peeces, &amp; to paye ſuch fine or fines as ſhalbe offered &amp; affered by the ſaid twelue expert men by vertue of their othes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one moitie of which fine or fines to be to the Maior of the ſayd cicie for the tyme being, &amp; to his ſucreſſours, and thother moytie to the wardeynes of the ſayd felowſhype for the tyme beynge, and to their ſucceſſours.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150877:31"/>
            <p>Prouided alwayes and be it further enacted by thauctoritie afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd, that yf any wardeyne or wardeynes for the time being, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid miſtery or occupation of makyng of ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, &amp; fuſtian of Naples, ſhall at any time hereafter ſeale, or cauſe to be ſea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led any ruſſels ſattens, ſattens reuerſes, or fuſtians of Naples, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhal not be well ſufficient, and truly wrought, and made, according to the true intent, and meanyng of this preſent act, ſhall forfeyte &amp; looſe for euery peece ſo ſealed, being not wel, ſufficient, and truly wrought and made, the whole value of euery ſuch pece ſo ſealed, thone halfe of whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che forfaytures to be to the kyng and Queenes maieſties, her heires and ſucceſſours, and thother moytie therof to be to ſuch perſon &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons, as ſhall ſue for the ſame by bill, action, or information, in anye of the kynges courtes of recorde, in which bil, action, or information no eſſoygne, prorection, or wager of lawe ſhalbe allowed.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An acte to confirme the liberties of the Lord Marchers in Wales.</head>
            <head type="sub">¶ The .xv. Chapter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Vmbly beſechen your excellent maieſties, your true &amp; faythful Subiectes, the Lordes marchers both ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuall and temporal, within your hyghneſſe dominio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of wales, that where as in a parliament holden at Weſt. the .xxvii. yeare of the reygne of king Henry theight, father vnto you our naturall Soueraigne Ladye, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monges other thynges, one act was made &amp; eſtabliſhed for lawes and iuſtice to be miniſtred in the ſayd dominion of wales, in lyke forme as it is in this realme of Englande, in the which acte, one article is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for that the lordes Marchers before y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> perliament, had vſed to put their tenauntes within their lordſhippes Marchers, vnder common main pryce &amp; ſuertie of apparaunce, and haue had the forfeytures thereof, which for euer, from, &amp; after the feaſt of all ſayntes, then next enſuing the ſaid parliament, ſhould vtterly ceaſe, and be determined. It was enacted, that after the ſaid feaſt of all ſayntes, euery lay, &amp; temporall perſon, then beyng a lorde marcher, ſhould haue the moytie or halfe of euery forfeyture of al and euery common mainprice, recogniſauce for the peace or apparance, ſorfeited by any of their tenauntes, inhabiti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g within any of theyr lordſhips Marchers, and they to be paied y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame moytie or halfe, by the handes of the ſhryffe of euery of the counties where ſuch forfeyture ſhalbe, yf the ſhiriffe can leuie the ſame, and the ſame ſhyryffe to accompt to our ſayde late Soueraygne lord y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kyng for the other halfe or moitie, in ſuch excheaker, as they be accomtant. And further it was enacted by thaucthoritie aforeſayd, that all, and euery lay, &amp; temporal perſon or perſons, then being lordes marchers, and hauing any lordſhipes marchers, or lordſhipes royals, ſhuld fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and after the ſayd feaſt of al ſaintes, haue al ſuch myſes and profytes
<pb n="xxxii" facs="tcp:150877:31"/>of theyr tenantes, as they haue had or vſed to haue, at the fyrſt entry into their landes in times paſt. And alſo ſhuld haue, hold, &amp; kepe, with in the precinct of their lordſhyppes, courres baron, courtes lete, and lawdayes, and al and euery thing to the ſayd courtes belonging, and alſo ſhuld haue within the precinct of theyr ſaid lordſhips, or lawdaye wayf, ſtrayf, infangechefe, outfangethefe, treaſure trouie, deodandes goodes, and cattels of fellons, &amp; of perſons condempned, or outlawed offellony or murther, put in exigent for fellony or murther, and alſo wrecke demer, wharfage, and cuſtomes of ſtraungers, as they haue had in tyme paſt, as though ſuch priuileges were graunted vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by poynt of charter, any thyng in that acte to the contrary notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, as in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd act of parliament more at large it may appeare.</p>
            <p>And foraſmuch as Byſhops, and other eccleſiaſtical perſons, beyng lordes marchers, hauing the lyke liberties, caſualties, profittes, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities within theyr lordſhips marchers, and lordſhips royal, with in the ſaid dominion, or principalitie of Wales, were not prouided for by the expreſſe letter of the ſayd Statute, in like ſorte, as the lay and temporall lordes marchers were: but rather of purpoſe, as it ſhould ſeme forgotten, and left out of the ſayde Acte, agaynſt all reaſon, and good equitie: And foraſmuch alſo, as the heires andſucceſſours of the lay &amp; temporal lordes marchers, then beyng, were not prouided for, by the limitation, and expreſſe wordes of the ſayd act, aſwel as theyr aunceſters, &amp; predeceſſers were, as reaſon wold they ſhuld haue ben.</p>
            <p>It may pleaſe your maieſties of your moſte gratious fauoureand benignitie, at the humble ſuit, and ſupplication of your ſayd faythful ſubiectes, the lordes marchers that now are, in the ſayd dommion of Wales, both ſpiritual and temporal, to graunt that it may by thaſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the lordes ſpiritual and temporal, and the commons in this preſent parliament aſſembled, be ordeyned, eſtabliſhed, and enacted, by thauc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of this preſent parliament, that aſwel your ſaid ſpiritual, &amp; ec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical ſubiectes, lordes marchers, now hauing lordſhippes mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, or lorſhyps royall in Wales aforeſaid, and theyr ſucceſſours, &amp; the ſucceſſours of euery of them, as alſo the heyres and ſucceſſoures of the lordes temporal marchers, that then were, or nowe be, and the heyres and ſucceſſours of euery of them, being or which herafter ſhal be, lordes marchers, within theyr lordſhips marchers, and lordſhips royals, in the dominion, or principalitie of Wales, ſhal haue, and enioy to them, &amp; to theyr heires, &amp; ſucceſſers, reſpectiuely, and ſeuerally for euer, the moyty &amp; half of euery forfayture, of al &amp; euery co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>price, recognifa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for the peace, or apparance forfeyted by any of their tena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, inhabiting within any of theyr lorſhips marchers, or lorſhips royal, &amp; they to be payed the ſame moyty or halfe, by the hands of the ſhyryffe of the countie, for the time being, after ſuch fourme &amp; forte, as the ſayd lay or temporal lordes marchers haue ben, or ought to haue
<pb facs="tcp:150877:32"/>ben payed the ſame, by force of the ſayde Statute.</p>
            <p>And further, ſhall haue al ſuch miſes, &amp; profits of theyr tenauntes, as the lordes marchers, ſpirituall or temporall, reſpectiuely, or ſeuerally had or vſed to haue at their fyrſt entry into their landes in times paſt before the makyng of the ſaid act or ſtatute. And alſo ſhal haue, hold, &amp; kepe within the precincte of theyr ſaid lordſhips, al ſuch courtes baron courtes lete, &amp; lawdayes, &amp; al and euery thing and thinges, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame courtes belonging, &amp; alſo ſhall haue within the precinct of their ſayde ſeuerall lordeſhyps, or lawdayes, al ſuch wayf ſtrayf, infangthefe, out fangthefe, treaſure trouis, deodandes, goodes, &amp; cattels of fellons, &amp; of perſons condempned or outlawed of felonie or murther, put in exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent for felony or murther, and alſo al ſuch wrecke demer, wharfage and cuſtomes of ſtraungers, as the lordes Marchers, ſpiritualll and temporal, reſpectiuely, and ſeuerally had and vſed in times paſt, before the makyng of the ſayde Statute.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An acte for the continuaunce of certayne ſtatutes. Cap. xvi.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in the parliament begon &amp; holden at London the .iii day of Nouember, in the .xxi. yeare of the reygne of oure moſt dread ſoueraigne lord of moſt famous memory, king Henry theyght, &amp; from thens adiourned to Weſtm. and there holden, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by diuers prorogations, vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſſolution therof, one act was made and eſtabliſhed, for the reſtraint of cariage &amp; conueying of horſes, and mares out of this realme &amp; alſo one other acte was there made, for the true wyndyng of wolles, and one other acte was there made, to reſtraine killing of wainlinges, bul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lockes, ſtieres, &amp; heyfers, being vnder thage of .ii. yeares which ſayd ſeueral actes were then made to endure &amp; continue to the next parlia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment, as by the ſaid ſeuerall actes ſhore plainly appeareth. And wher alſo in the ſame parliament, one other act was made &amp; eſtabliſhed, for attaintes to be ſued, for the punyſhment of periury, vpon vntrue ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dites, which actes laſt before rehearſed, were then made &amp; ordeined, to continue &amp; endure to the laſt day of the next parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as bi y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame act more playnly at large is ſhewed &amp; may appeare. And wher alſo in the parliament begon &amp; holden at Weſtm. theight day of Iune, in the xxviii. yeare of the reygne of our ſayd moſt drad ſouereigne lord king Henry theight, &amp; there continued and kept, vntil the diſſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof it was ordeyned &amp; enacted, that all &amp; ſinguler the ſaid actes aboue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, &amp; euery of them, ſhould continue &amp; endure in their ſorce &amp; ſtrength, &amp; alſo be obſerued &amp; kept vntyl the laſt day of the next par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, as by the ſame act amonges other thinges, therin conteined more playnely appeareth. And where alſo in the parliament begon &amp; holden at Weſt. the .xxviii. day of Aprill in the .xxxi. yeare of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reigne of our ſaid late moſt dread ſoueraigne Lord, king Henry theight, and
<pb n="xxxiiii" facs="tcp:150877:32"/>there continued vntyl the .xxviiii. day of Iune then next folowing, it was ordeyned and enacted by thauctoritie of the ſame parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al &amp; ſinguler the ſayd ſeuerall actes aboue remembred &amp; euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; al clauſes, articles, &amp; prouiſions in them, &amp; euery of them contayned, ſhuld continue &amp; endure in their force &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, and alſo be obſerued &amp; kept vntyl the laſt day of the next parliament, as by the ſame act a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monges other thinges therin contayned, more playnely appeareth. And where in the parliament holden at Weſtm. in the .xxxv. yeare of the reigne of our ſayde late ſoueraygne lord kyng Henry theight, one act was made for the preſeruatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of woods, to endure for .vii. yeares then next folowing, &amp; from thence to thend of the next parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as by the ſame act more playnly doth &amp; may appeare. And where alſo at the parliament holden at Weſt. in the xxxvii. yeare of the reigne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid, king Henry theight, &amp; ther continued and kept vntil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof it was ordeyned &amp; enacted, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al &amp; ſinguler the ſaid actes aboue mentioned, &amp; euery of them excepte the ſayd act made for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of woods, as is aforeſaid, ſhuld continue &amp; endure in their force &amp; ſtrength, &amp; alſo to be obſerued &amp; kept, vntil the laſt day of the next par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liament then folowing, as vi the ſame act amonges other things ther in conteined more playnely appereth. And wher alſo at the ſeſſion of the parliament, ended at Weſt. in the .xiiii. day of March, in the third yeare of the reygne of our ſouereigne Lord kyng Edwarde the .vi. one acte was made for the true currying of leather, whiche acte was made to endure to thend of the next parliament, as by the ſame acte more playnely appeareth. And where alſo at the ſeſſion of a parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ended at Weſtm. the firſt day of February, in the fourth yeare of the reygne of our ſayd late ſoueraygne Lord king Edward the .vi one act was then &amp; there made, concerning the buying of rother bea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes. And alſo one other act was then &amp; there made touchyng the buy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing &amp; ſelling of butter &amp; cheſe, which ſayd ſeuerall actes were then &amp; there made, to endure and continue, to thend of the next parliament, as by the ſame ſeuerall actes more at large it doth and may appeare. And where alſo at the ſeſſion of a parliament by prorogation holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Weſt, the .xxiii. day of Ianuary in the .v. year of the reigne of our ſaid ſoueraigne lord, one other acte was then and there made, againſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratours and forſtallers, to endure to thend of the next parliament, which al &amp; ſinguler the ſaid actes aboue mentioned together, with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid act concerning the preſeruation of woods, at a parliament holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Weſtm. the fyrſt day of March, in the .vii. yeare of the raygne of our ſayd ſoueraygne Lord kyng Edward the .vi. &amp; there continued and diſſolued the laſt day of the ſame moneth of Marh, &amp; al clauſes articles &amp; prouiſions in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; euery of them conteyned were there re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiued &amp; continued, to ſtande in their force &amp; ſtrength, vntil the laſt dai of the next parliament. And where alſo at the ſeſſion of a parliament holden by prorogatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Weſt. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xxiiii. day of October, in the .i. yeare
<pb facs="tcp:150877:33"/>of the raygne of our moſt gratious ſoueraygne lady y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quene, &amp; there continued &amp; kept vntil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſſolution therof, one act was there made &amp; eſtabliſhed againſt vnlawful &amp; rebellious aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bles, to endure to thend of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> next parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame act more plainli doth, &amp; mai appeare. And where alſo at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſeſſion of parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, laſt before me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned, al &amp; ſinguler y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> actes aboue mentioned, &amp; before that time co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued at ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dry parliaments, as is aforeſayde, &amp; clauſes, articles, &amp; prouiſions in them, &amp; euery of them conteined, were ther reuiued, and continued to ſtand in their force &amp; ſtrength, vnto the laſt day of the next parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
            <p>Foraſmuch as al &amp; ſinguler the ſaid ſeuerall actes aboue mentioned, be good &amp; beneficial for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> welth of this realme. Be it therefore enacted, ordeined, &amp; eſtabliſhed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> king &amp; quene our ſoueraygn lord &amp; lady, with thaſſent of the lordes ſpirituall &amp; te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall, &amp; the commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in this preſent parliament aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled, &amp; by thauctoritie of the ſame, that al &amp; ſinguler the ſayd ſeuerall actes and eſtatutes aboue mentioned, &amp; rehearſed, &amp; euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and al clauſes articles, &amp; prouiſions in them &amp; euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teined, ſhalbe reuiued, continued, ſtand, &amp; endure in theyr force &amp; ſtrength, to al intentes, conſtructions, &amp; purpoſes &amp; ſhal be obſerued &amp; kept in al thinges, vntil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt day of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> next parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="chapter">
            <head>¶ An acte touchinge leaſes hereafter to be made by certayne ſpirituall perſons. Cap. xvii.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here in the parliament begon &amp; holden at Weſt. the eight day of Iune, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .xxviii. year of the raigne of our late king of famous memory Henry theight, &amp; there co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued &amp; kept vntil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diſſolution of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame parliamet, the .xviii. day of Iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne next folowing, one acte intituled, an act for reſtitution of the fyrſte fruites in the tyme of vacation, to the next incu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bent, was had &amp; made, wherin are certayn clauſes for leaſes then made, &amp; to be made bi ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tual &amp; eccleſiaſtical perſons, to endure, &amp; be in force for terme of .vi. ye ares if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> incu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bentes did reſigne their ſaid ſpiritual promotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, or if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſhuld otherwiſe become void by thouli act of the ſame thincu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ben<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, as by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame act more at large may appeare. To thintent the per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons and vicars and others, hauing cure of ſoules, may the better at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende, and be the more vigilaunt in their miniſtery and function.</p>
            <p>Be it enacted by the king our ſoueraigne lord, &amp; the quene our ſoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raygne lady with thaſſentes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes ſpiritual &amp; te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral, &amp; the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mons in this preſent parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aſſembled, &amp; by thauctoritie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> aſmuch of the ſame act, as doth concerne the makyng good of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaid leaſes, ne any clauſe, ſentence, prouiſion, or article therin conteined ſhal extend, or be conſtrued, or adiudged to extende to any leaſe, that ſhalbe made by any perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vicar or any other hauing any ſpiritual pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>motion, after the feaſt of the purification of our Lady next co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minge.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>Excuſum Londini in aedibus Iohannis Cawodi, Tipographi Regiae Maieſtatis.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Anno.</hi> M.D.LV.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:150877:33"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
